<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A fourth letter to a person of quality, being an historical account of the doctrine of the Sacrament, from the primitive times to the Council of Trent shewing the novelty of transubstantiation.</title>
            <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 168 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53955</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1081</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R274</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13062019</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13062019</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97031</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53955)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97031)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 395:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A fourth letter to a person of quality, being an historical account of the doctrine of the Sacrament, from the primitive times to the Council of Trent shewing the novelty of transubstantiation.</title>
                  <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 77, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ben. Griffin, and are to be sold by Randal Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by Edward Pelling. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Advertisements: p. [2]-[3] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Transubstantiation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97031:1"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:97031:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
A FOURTH LETTER TO A PERSON of QUALITY, BEING AN HISTORICAL ACCOUNT OF THE DOCTRINE OF THE SACRAMENT, From the PRIMITIVE Times, TO THE COUNCIL of <hi>TRENT;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SHEWING The NOVELTY of Tranſubſtantiation,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Ben. Griffin,</hi> and are to be Sold by <hi>Randal Taylor,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:97031:2"/>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Liber cui Titulus.</hi> (A Fourth Letter to a Perſon of Quality.)</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>May 17th. 1688.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>H. Maurice R<hi rend="sup">mo.</hi> in Chriſto P. D. Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>helmo Archiep. Cant. à Sacris.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97031:2"/>
            <head>A FOURTH LETTER TO A Person of Quality; BEING AN HISTORICAL ACCOUNT, OF THE DOCTRINE OF THE SACRAMENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I HAVE been longer in your Debt than I inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, when I laſt engaged my Credit to you. I hope now to give you ſatisfaction in full; but you muſt not expect Intereſt to make the payment <hi>ſwell,</hi> becauſe the thing I am accountable to you for is ſo Trite and worn, that I think it a kindneſs to you to make as <hi>ſhort</hi> payment as is poſſible, becauſe 'twill ſave you the trouble of Examining a world of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97031:3"/>
ſmall quotations, which is worſe than the telling of <hi>odd</hi> and <hi>broken</hi> Mony. I promiſed you an account of the Doctrine of the Holy <hi>Sacrament;</hi> which the Church of Rome hath turned at laſt into the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Tranſubſtantiation; By which they mean, that upon the Prieſts Conſecration of the Bread and Wine, the Subſtance of them is turn'd into Chriſt's Natural Fleſh and Blood, nothing remaining but the Species, and Properties of the Elements; that is, the Smell, the Taſte, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This abſurd Doctrine being ſo repugnant to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to Reaſon, and to the very Senſes of Mankind, their main buſineſs is to delude poor People into an Opinion, that it was the ſenſe of the Primitive Churches of Chriſt. We are deſirous to come to a fair <hi>Tryal</hi> of this matter, and that I may do my part towards it, I ſhall endeavour to bring it to a very ſhort iſſue by this Method.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall ſhew you the Faith of the Ancient Churches, from a long Controverſie they had with thoſe Hereticks, the <hi>Apollinarians</hi> and <hi>Eutychians:</hi> Which being undeniable and publick matter of <hi>Fact,</hi> will clear up the ſenſe of the Ancients far better than ſingle, broken paſſages out of the Fathers, which Men of parts know how to interpret to their own advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſhall ſhew you when and how the ſenſe of the Ancient Church came to be <hi>alter'd,</hi> what Progreſs that alteration <hi>made,</hi> and what ſtrong oppoſition it met with for ſeveral Ages after it began. And by this plain Hiſtorical Account, you will eaſily diſcern what an <hi>Innovation</hi> the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation is.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And then I ſhall give a Summary Anſwer to thoſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97031:3"/>
things which the Modern Romaniſts do urge out of the Fathers, by ſhewing you the Genuine meaning of them, which they by wreſting, or by not underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them rightly, have uſed to deceive the world with falſe Notions.</p>
            <p n="1">I. As for the Faith of the Ancient Churches it will ſoon appear, if you do but obſerve this <hi>One</hi> thing, and bear it carefully in your mind. About the year of Chriſt, 370. or a little before, <hi>Apollinarius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> had ſpread about this Heretical Opinion, that the humanity of Chriſt was turned and ſwallowed up into the Deity? ſo that tho his two Natures were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct before the Union, yet by and upon the Union, they became one Nature, his humane part being <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted</hi> or <hi>Tranſubſtantiated</hi> into the Divine, the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties</hi> only and <hi>appearance</hi> of Humane Body remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. This indeed was not <hi>all</hi> his Hereſie, for he aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed too, that Chriſt took a Body without a Rational Soul, the Deity ſupplying the place of it; and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other ſtrange Opinions he held, to the great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance of the Church. But it is too notorious to need any proof, that this was part of <hi>Apollinarius</hi> his Hereſie, that upon the Union of Chriſts two Natures, his Manhood was <hi>changed</hi> into his Divinity, ſaving only the <hi>Properties</hi> of it; ſo that, he was forced to yield, that the <hi>Deity</hi> was <hi>Circumciſed,</hi> and <hi>ſuffered</hi> upon the Croſs, in the <hi>appearance,</hi> or (if you will have it in the Language of the Romaniſts) under the <hi>Species</hi> of Humane Fleſh.</p>
            <p>Within the compaſs of Twenty Years, <hi>Apollinarius</hi> his Hereſie was condemned by Three Councils, at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria,</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> and at <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> But about Sixty Seven years after, I mean <hi>Anno</hi> 448. it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97031:4"/>
by <hi>Eutyches,</hi> a Presbyter at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> whoſe poſitive Opinion was, that the two Natures of Chriſt being United, the ſubſtance of the one utterly <hi>ceaſed,</hi> his Humanity being quite <hi>converted</hi> into his Divinity, ſo that nothing was left of his Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but the <hi>Qualities</hi> and <hi>Accidents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Hereſie, begun by <hi>Apollinarius,</hi> and promoted by <hi>Eutyches,</hi> laſted a long time; and 'tis very well worth your Obſervation, how nearly it <hi>reſembles</hi> the Romiſh Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation in the Sacrament. For as our Adverſaries hold, that the Subſtance of Bread and Wine is upon Conſecration turned into the very Subſtance of Chriſt's Fleſh and Blood, nothing of them remaining but the Accidents; ſo the <hi>Apolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narians</hi> and <hi>Eutychians</hi> held, that the Subſtance of Chriſt's Humane Nature was, upon its Union, turned into the Subſtance of his Divinity, nothing of his Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity remaining but the Qualities and Properties. As <hi>theſe</hi> hold, that the very Subſtance of Chriſt's Body and Blood is received under the Species of Bread and Wine; ſo <hi>thoſe</hi> Hereticks held, that the very Deity <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide Hiſtor. Council</hi> Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. <hi>in</hi> init. <hi>&amp;</hi> Leonis <hi>ep. 17. ad</hi> Maxim. <hi>part 3. iſtius Concilii.</hi>
               </note> of Chriſt was Born, and did Grow, Suffer, Dye and Riſe again under the Species of Humane Fleſh: Or, briefly, that Chriſt appeared not in the Truth or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Humane Nature, but only in the outward <hi>Form</hi> and <hi>Figure</hi> of a Man; his Humanity being tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiated as they preſumed into his Divinity, all but the Idea of it.</p>
            <p>Now among many Arguments which the Ancients uſed againſt thoſe Hereticks, ſome of the Greateſt Men in the Church drew <hi>One</hi> Argument from the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>Sacrament;</hi> and made uſe of <hi>Our</hi> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple againſt Tranſubſtantiation, to expoſe the Hereſie of the <hi>Apollinarians</hi> and <hi>Eutychians;</hi> which plainly ſhews,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97031:4"/>
that <hi>Our</hi> Opinion as to the Holy Sacrament, was in thoſe times the <hi>received</hi> Opinion of the Catholick Church.</p>
            <p>To prove this particularly: St. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> writing to his old Acquaintance <hi>Caeſarius</hi> to reclaim him from the <hi>Apollinarian</hi> Hereſie, into which he had unluckily fallen, among other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments he uſed to convince him, he drew a <hi>parallel</hi> from the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> to ſhew, that Chriſt had two di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct <hi>Natures</hi> in one <hi>Perſon. As,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>before Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration we call it Bread, but the Divine Grace having ſanctified it by the Prayer of the Prieſt, it is no longer called Bread, but is thought worthy to be called the Lords Body, altho the Nature of Bread remains in it, and we do not ſay there be two Bodies, but one Body of the Son; ſo here, the Divine Nature (of Chriſt) being joyned to the Humane, they both make one Son and one Perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You muſt know, that the <hi>Greek</hi> Copy of this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle is not yet come to light: Very probably it is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt by thoſe, who know how to ſuppreſs many things which hurt their Cauſe, But a Latin Copy of it was found in Archbiſhop <hi>Cranmer</hi>'s time in a Libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry at <hi>Florence</hi> by <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> who brought a Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript of it with him into <hi>England,</hi> and put it into the Archbiſhops Library. And this paſſage in it is ſuch a ſtabbing blow to the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, that the Romaniſts have turn'd and twin'd themſelves every way to evade the force of it, were it poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>Firſt they denied this Epiſtle to be St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>'s. But this pretence has been ſince thrown out of doors by ſome learned Doctors of the Roman Church her ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:97031:5"/>
               <hi>Stephen Gardiner,</hi> that diſſembling and bloudy Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> being ſomewhat conſcious to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that this Epiſtle was <hi>Genuine,</hi> pretended Secondly, that by the Nature of Bread which St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith remains, he meant not the <hi>Subſtance,</hi> but the <hi>Accidents</hi> and <hi>Properties</hi> of it: wherein he was fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and divers others; and this is pretended ſtill by ſome Popiſh Writers here in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> now. But this is flatly to contradict the plaineſt and moſt <hi>natural</hi> expreſſions in the world. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides it utterly overthrows the great <hi>deſign</hi> of St. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome:</hi> for his purpoſe was to ſhew <hi>Ceſarius,</hi> that the Subſtance of Chriſts Humanity remained after its uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Deity; for this was the thing in <hi>diſpute</hi> with the <hi>Apollinarians.</hi> They owned the <hi>Accidents,</hi> the <hi>Properties,</hi> the <hi>Qualities</hi> of Humanity to remain in Chriſt, but affirm'd the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of his Humane Nature to be turned into the Deity. So that had St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> meant, that the Accidents only of Bread remained in the Sacrament, the example would not have been to the purpoſe, nor would the Argument have had any force at all, but St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> would have proved himſelf the moſt weak and impertinent man at reaſoning that could be. I will give you the words of a learned and moderate perſon of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <note place="margin">A Treatiſe of Tranſubſtant.</note> Communion now living, whoſe Book, I hope, you have by you. St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith plainly, <q>that the Nature of Bread abideth after conſecration; and this Fathers Argument would be of no validity, if this Nature of the Bread were nothing but in ſhew; for <hi>Appollinarius</hi> might have made another op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite Argument, and ſay, that indeed it might be ſaid there were two Natures in Jeſus Chriſt, but that the Humane Nature was only in appearance,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97031:5"/>
as the Bread in the Euchariſt is, but in ſhew, and hath only outward and viſible Qualities remaining in it, whereby it is termed to be Bread.</q>
            </p>
            <p>One thing more I will obſerve to you, concerning this Epiſtle, to ſhew how injuriouſly ſome have dealt with St. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> and how thoſe men ſpeak againſt their own Conſciences when they tell us, as they have often done, that this great man is on their ſide, A few years ago the learned Mounſieur <hi>Bigotius</hi> found this Epiſtle at <hi>Florence,</hi> and <hi>Anno</hi> 1680. printed it in his Edition of <hi>Palladius</hi> with the beſt Apology he could make for this paſſage. But when the Book was now ready to be publiſhed, ſome of the <hi>Sorbon</hi> Doctors fraudulently cut out this Epiſtle, and <hi>Bigotins</hi> his Preface to it. What an Art is this, firſt to cut out an Authors Tongue for ſpeaking againſt them, and yet to pretend that he ſpake on their behalf? Yet it was not ſo cunningly done, but that the abuſe was complain'd of; and by good Providence the Leaves which were thus ſhamefully cut out, are lately fallen into the hands of a learned man of our Church, who hath given us a full and particular account of this whole matter, in his excellent <hi>Defence of the Expoſition of the Doctrine of the Church of</hi> England, to which I refer you for your more ample ſatisfaction, both as to the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle it ſelf, and as to the ſtrength of St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>'s Argument againſt the <hi>Apollinarians,</hi> which utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation.</p>
            <p>To go on now with our Hiſtorical Account. Our next ancient Writer is <hi>Theodoret,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Cyrus</hi> in <hi>Syria,</hi> a great Man at the Council of <hi>Chalcedon, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 451. and without controverſie one of the moſt learned Men of that Age.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:97031:6"/>
The Hereſie of <hi>Apollinarus</hi> had now been eſpouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Eutyches</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople: Theodoret</hi> undertook the quarrel and wrote excellently againſt the <hi>Eutychi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> by way of <hi>Dialogue:</hi> and among ſeveral other ſtrong Arguments he drew an example from the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Euchariſt, as St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> had done before him. I think it is my beſt way to lay before you that part of the <hi>Dialogue,</hi> which chiefly concerns us, nakedly as it lies in <hi>Theodoret;</hi> only you muſt remember that 'tis between <hi>Orthodoxus</hi> and <hi>Eraniſtes;</hi> now <hi>Orthodoxus</hi> perſonates the Catholick, and <hi>Eraniſtes</hi> the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick; the former held, that Chriſt had two Natures in one Perſon; the latter, that his Humane Nature, was abſorpt, and ſubſtantially changed into his Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
            <q>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eran.</speaker>
                  <p>It is neceſſary to turn every ſtone, as the Proverb is, that Truth may be found, eſpecially in Divine Matters.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Tell me then; thoſe myſtical Symbols which are offered by the Prieſts (at the Euchariſt) what are they repreſentations of?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eran.</speaker>
                  <p>Of the Lords Body and Bloud.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Of a True, or not of a True Body?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eran.</speaker>
                  <p>Of a True Body.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Right; for there muſt be an Original of a Copy; for even Painters imitate Nature, and draw Pictures of things that are ſeen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eran.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis true.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>If then the Divine Myſteries be the Simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes (or Figures) of a True Body, then is the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of our Lord even now a True Body, not chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the Nature of the Divinity, but filled with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Glory.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eran.</speaker>
                  <p>You have ſpoken very ſeaſonably of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97031:6"/>
Divine Myſteries (or Sacrament:) For I will from thence ſhew the Converſion of our Lords Body into another Nature: Anſwer my queſtions therefore.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>I will Anſwer.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eran.</speaker>
                  <p>What do you call the Gift that is Offered before the Invocation of the Prieſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod</speaker>
                  <p>We are not to ſpeak plainly leaſt ſome ſhould be here that are not ſufficiently inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eran.</speaker>
                  <p>Anſwer then Aenigmatically.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſay then, it is Nouriſhment from <hi>certain</hi> Seeds.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eran.</speaker>
                  <p>But how do we call one of the Symbols?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, it is a common Name that ſignifies a kind of Drink.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eran.</speaker>
                  <p>But what do you call thoſe things after Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>The Body of Chriſt, and the Blood of Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eran</speaker>
                  <p>And do you believe that you participate of Chriſt's Body and Blood?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, I believe ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eran.</speaker>
                  <p>As then the Symbols of our Lords Body and Blood are other things before the Prieſts Invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but after Invocation are changed, and become other things; even ſo was the Lords Body after its Aſſumption changed into the Divine Subſtance.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>You are taken in the Nets, which you your ſelf have made; for the Myſtical Symbols do not in any wiſe paſs out of their own Nature, no not <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Theod. Dialogue. 2.</note> after Conſecration; for they remain in their own former Subſtance, and figure, and kind, and are to be Seen and Touched as they were before.</p>
               </sp>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:97031:7"/>
Nothing can be plainer than this to Men who are not obſtinately addicted to an Opinion in ſpight of all Reaſon and Senſe. And what <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoret</hi> ſaith here, is very agreeable to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what he told <hi>Eraniſtes</hi> in the Firſt Dialogue, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>our Saviour honoured the viſible Symbols with the Appellation of his Body and Blood, not changing the Nature of them, but adding Grace to Nature.</hi> To avoid all this, our Adverſaries pretend, that by Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and Nature <hi>Theodoret</hi> means the <hi>Accidents</hi> of Bread; which is in effect to tell us, that they are utterly reſolved to <hi>believe,</hi> or at leaſt to <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friend</hi> a <hi>Lie:</hi> For who, that really loves Truth, would thus <hi>confound</hi> things, ſo as to make Subſtance and Accident the <hi>ſame?</hi> But if they will ſtrain their parts to play tricks with words, how can they make this their interpretation to come up to <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoret</hi>'s <hi>deſign,</hi> or to reach the Argument he had in hand, which was about the ſuppoſed ſubſtantial change of Chriſt's Humane Nature into his Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? <hi>Theodorets</hi> purpoſe was to Confute this by Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing from the Doctrine of the Sacrament; and had the Church believed a Subſtantial change of the Bread, this would have <hi>confirm'd</hi> the <hi>Eutychian</hi> in his Opinion, but it could not have Confuted it: For the Heretick deſired no more to be granted him, but this, that the Nature, or Subſtance of the Elements doth <hi>ceaſe,</hi> though the <hi>Accidents</hi> continue: And this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed would have favour'd his conceit, that the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Chriſt's Humanity did ceaſe, the Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of it Remaining ſtill: But <hi>Theodoret</hi> could not be ſo weak as to yield this; for then he would ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitably have loſt himſelf in his Diſpute.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:97031:7"/>
But what think you of a <hi>Pope</hi> that diſputed againſt the <hi>Eutychians</hi> too, and that from the very ſame Doctrine of the Sacrament? It was no leſs a Man than <hi>Gelaſius,</hi> who was Biſhop of <hi>Rome Anno</hi> 492. and wrote a Celebrated Book of <hi>the two Natures in Chriſt:</hi> Which though <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and ſome more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Bellarmine</hi>'s time denied to be this <hi>Galaſius</hi> his Book, yet the Arguments againſt them are ſo ſtrong, that Cardinal <hi>Perron, Petavius</hi> and other Learned and more Ingenuous Men ſince, have yielded us that point: And the moderate Writer I quoted before, ſaith, <hi>This Work is aſſuredly of Pope</hi> Gelaſius, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In that piece of <hi>Gelaſius</hi> his Book which we have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant <note place="margin">Treatiſe of Tranſub. <hi>p.</hi> 40.</note> in the <hi>Bibliotheca Patrum,</hi> he teacheth the ſame Doctrine which <hi>Theodoret</hi> did, and for the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſame thing, as Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine</hi> doth <note place="margin">Bellarm. <hi>de Euch.</hi> lib. 2. cap. 27.</note> confeſs. And what can be plainer than theſe words of <hi>Gelaſius?</hi> Viz. <hi>That the Sacraments which we receive of the Body and Blood</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Certè Sacramenta quae ſumimus Corporis &amp; Sanguinis Domini di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vina res eſt, propter quod &amp; per eadem divinae efficimur conſortes naturae; &amp; tamen eſſe non deſinit Subſtantia vel Natura Panis &amp; Vini,</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>of the Lord is a Divine thing, becauſe by them we are made partakers of the Divine Nature; and yet the Substance or Nature of the Bread and Wine doth not ceaſe to be. And truly the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation and Similitude of Chriſt's Body and Blood is Celebrated in the Miniſtration of theſe Myſteries; and therefore it is plain that we muſt think that of Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, which we profeſs and Celebrate in this Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him.</hi> His meaning evidently is, that we muſt believe the Permanency of Chriſt's Humane Nature, though united to the Divine, becauſe in the Holy Euchariſt, which is the <hi>Repreſentation</hi> of Chriſt, the Nature and <hi>Subſtance</hi> of Bread and Wine remaineth, though Conſecrated by the Miniſter.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:97031:8"/>
And yet we have another eminent Writer on our ſide, no leſs a Man than <hi>Ephram,</hi> who was Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch of <hi>Anti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch</hi> about <hi>Anno</hi> 540. <hi>He</hi> diſputed too a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Eutychians,</hi> and drew the very <hi>ſame</hi> Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the Sacrament which others had uſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, ſhewing, that the Humanity of Chriſt did not Ceaſe in its Subſtance by being united to the word, no more than the Bread ceaſeth in its Subſtance by the Addition of Spiritual Grace. <hi>That</hi> (ſays he) <note place="margin">Phetii Biblio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thee. cod 229.</note> 
               <hi>which is received by the Faithful doth not depart out of its own ſenſible Subſtance and yet continues undivided from the intelligible Grace.</hi> And leaſt it ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed (though 'tis ſtrange it ſhould) that by <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> he means the <hi>Species</hi> and <hi>Accidents</hi> of the Bread, he ſays the ſame thing of the Sacrament of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> where no Romaniſt ever affirmed any Tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation to be. His words are theſe; <hi>Baptiſm alſo, which becomes entirely a Spiritual thing, and is One, doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ſtill the propriety of the ſenſible Subſtance. I mean Water, and loſeth not what it was,</hi> Whence 'tis clear, that <hi>Ephram</hi> lookt upon the caſe in both Sacraments to be the <hi>ſame,</hi> an Addition of Spiritual Grace to be in <hi>both,</hi> but a loſs of Subſtance to be in <hi>neither,</hi> nor any other change to be in the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> than what is in <hi>Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, I have inſtanced in thoſe four Writers particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, not only becauſe they were all Great Men in their Times, (Three of them <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> nay one of them Patriarch of <hi>Rome)</hi> but becauſe they all argued againſt the <hi>ſame</hi> Hereſie after the <hi>ſame</hi> manner; which to me ſeems very obſervable and <hi>providential:</hi> For tho the <hi>Eutychian</hi> Hereſie prevailed ſo long, and did ſpread ſo far, that it did vaſt miſchief, yet God dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the iſſues of it ſo, that 'twas an <hi>occaſion</hi> of ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97031:8"/>
us what the Catholick Faith was, both in the Greek and Latin Churches, in thoſe moſt Learned and flouriſhing times of Chriſtianity, concerning <hi>that great</hi> point which in theſe latter Ages hath made ſo many diſtractions in Chriſtendom. For it is not to be imagined, but that theſe Eminent Biſhops ſpake the ſenſe of the whole Catholick Church, over which they preſided. For having to do with obſtinate He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, they were obliged to encounter them upon principles which all Chriſtians <hi>conſented</hi> to, and were <hi>agreed;</hi> otherwiſe the Diſputations would have been <hi>Endleſs,</hi> had they argued from principles of their <hi>own,</hi> and which they were ſtill to prove. It was neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for them to proceed upon ſome <hi>common</hi> Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereon both Hereticks and Catholicks did ſtand, and ſuch was this Doctrine of the Sacrament; for which Reaſon the Learned Doctors of the Church choſe to inſiſt upon it; nor do I find that the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks did contradict it, or endeavour to deſtroy it; which they would moſt certainly have done (conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering how much it made againſt them) had they not known it to have been a principle, univerſally <hi>receiv'd,</hi> that the Bread and Wine are <hi>not</hi> Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiated, but remain ſtill in their own <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Subſtance,</hi> even after Conſecration.</p>
            <p>For this Reaſon I have omitted an hundred other quotations out of the Ancients, and have taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice only of this their <hi>common</hi> Argument againſt the <hi>Eutychians,</hi> becauſe I think it a <hi>plain</hi> and <hi>conciſe</hi> way of confuting the Popiſh pretence, touching the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation. For it is not imaginable that the Ancients would have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſo peremptorily and <hi>dogmatically</hi> in this point, had they not had the Authority of the whole Church
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97031:9"/>
to have back't them: And becauſe they ſpake this ſo <hi>freely,</hi> and that as a <hi>common</hi> Argument againſt thoſe Learned Hereticks, we may be ſure, that what they ſaid was the <hi>common Faith of the Catholick Church</hi> in thoſe times; I mean in the Sixth Century.</p>
            <p>And now, Sir, I ſhall proceed to Examine, how the matter ſtood as to this point in the times follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. It is evident, that the great Council of 338. Fathers, who met at <hi>Conſtantinople, Anno</hi> 754. were of this Faith, <hi>That the Bread in the Euchariſt is not Chriſt himſelf, but the Image of him.</hi> For this they urg'd, as an Argument againſt the uſe of all <hi>other</hi> I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, becauſe the Symbols in the Euchariſt are <hi>the only Image of himſelf which he left his Church.</hi> Now this utterly overthrows the Doctrine of the <hi>Corporal preſence</hi> (and much rather the conceit of <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation.)</hi> For if the Bread be the Image of his Body, it cannot be the Body it <hi>ſelf,</hi> as the Second <hi>Nicene</hi> Council argued, when they oppos'd the Definitions of this Council at <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> And beſides, there is ſomething very obſervable in the Diſcourſe of this Council upon this point, which I wonder ſo many Writers have not taken notice of, and it is this, that <hi>Chriſt Ordaining at his laſt Supper this Image of himſelf, intended to ſhew the Myſtery of his Incarnation.</hi> And to this purpoſe they expreſt themſelves, as any one may ſee by conſulting the Acts of the Council; <hi>As</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conc.</hi> Nic. 2. Act. 6.</note> 
               <hi>when Chriſt took our Nature, he took barely the matter of Humane Subſtance, not his whole Perſon, Divinity and all; for to ſuppoſe that would be an Offence, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation to the Deity; ſo when he appointed this Image of himſelf, he choſe barely the Subſtance of Bread, not any ſhape of Man in it but only a Repreſentation of his Natural Fleſh; for that would have been an Intreduction of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry.</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:97031:9"/>
Moreover they ſay, <hi>that as Chriſt's Natural Body was Holy by being filled with the Deity; ſo this I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of him becomes Holy, by being Sanctified by Grace; and as that Fleſh of ours, which Chriſt took, became Sanctified by being united to the Deity, ſo is the Bread in the Euchariſt (the true Image of his Natural Fleſh) Sanctified by the Advent of the Holy Spirit,</hi> &amp;c. Is this at all conſiſtent with Tranſubſtantiation, or with the Doctrine of Chriſt's Corporal preſence in the Sacrament? And yet this was the ſenſe of thoſe 338. Fathers which they Dogmatically deliver'd as the ſenſe of the Church, whereof they lookt upon themſelves as the Repreſentatives. Therefore Cardinal <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> underſtanding their ſenſe throughly, and finding how ſtrongly and invincibly it made againſt Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, had no other way left him but to rank this great Council among Hereticks; nay, he ſays they were the firſt, that ever called in queſtion <hi>the Truth of the Lords Body in the Euchariſt.</hi> Now this <note place="margin">Bellarm. <hi>de Euchar.</hi> l. 1. c. 1.</note> is eaſily ſaid; but by his favour, they denied not the <hi>reality</hi> of Chriſt's <hi>Spiritual</hi> preſence, but of his <hi>Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> preſence only, as we Proteſtants do. Nay he himſelf rightly obſerves in the ſame place, that the Proteſtant Faith in this point was not reckon'd among any of the Ancient Hereſies, nor ſo much as <hi>diſputed</hi> againſt by any one of the Ancients for the firſt 600. Years. For how ſhould any Diſpute againſt that, which was the Common Faith of the Church, and had been ſo all along, to the time of this <hi>Conſtantinopolitan</hi> Council? Thoſe Fathers did no more but declare that publickly, which they had received from former A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and now made uſe of as a proper Argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Images.</p>
            <p>The Patrons of Images finding themſelves pinch't
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97031:10"/>
with this Argument, began to move a point which hitherto lay quiet, and to ſtrain thoſe words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> to a ſenſe beyond what had been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly taught, though it was a great while before they could hammer out their New Notions into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Form; for they ſpake very confuſedly, inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtently, and groſly, as if Chriſt's Natural Body were in the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>And though I do not find that any of them went ſo far as to own yet a Subſtantial change of the Nature of the Bread and Wine into the Subſtance of Fleſh and Blood (which is the conceit of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> now) yet 'tis plain, that what theſe Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors ſaid, cauſed a New Great Controverſie in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom, and that juſt upon the neck of the former Quarrel about Images, whereof I have already gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you a particular and Faithful account.</p>
            <p n="2">II. And now I am come to the Second Thing I promiſed to ſhew you; which was, when, and how the ſenſe of the Ancient Church about the Sacrament, came to be <hi>alter'd,</hi> what <hi>progreſs</hi> that alteration made, and what ſtrong <hi>Oppoſition</hi> it met with for ſeveral A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges after it began.</p>
            <p>It is generally agreed, that <hi>Paſchaſius Rathbertus</hi> was one of the firſt Innovators in the Latin Church, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Albertin. <hi>de Sacram.</hi> p. 920.</note> about <hi>Anno</hi> 818. He was firſt a Monk, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Abbot of <hi>Corbey</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and a Man of ſome conſiderable Reputation (eſpecially for thoſe times, when Learning was moſt decayed,) which perhaps might tranſport him into an undue Opinion of his own abilities; and that might make him affect ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity. However it came about, two very Learned Jeſuites are agreed, that <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> was a <hi>Leading Man</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:97031:10"/>
in this buſineſs, So ſays <hi>Bellarmine, that</hi> Paſchaſius <note place="margin">Bellarm. <hi>de Scriptor. Eccleſ. in</hi> Paſchaſ. &amp; Sirmond. <hi>in vita</hi> Paſchaſii <hi>operibus ejus prefix.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>was the firſt Author that wrote ſeriouſly and copiouſly of the Truth of the Lords Body and Blood in the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt.</hi> And ſo ſaith <hi>Sirmondus, that</hi> Paſchaſius <hi>was the first that explained the Genuine ſenſe of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> (he means the Roman) <hi>Church ſo as that he ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the way to others, who afterwards wrote upon the ſame Subject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Book which they chiefly mean, is that <hi>of the Body and Blood of the Lord,</hi> written to one <hi>Placidus,</hi> a young man whom <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> dearly loved. In read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Book one ſhall find ſo many dark Riddles, unconquerable perplexities, and plain inconſiſtences, that it may be juſtly queſtioned, whether they are poſſible to be reconciled to Truth or Senſe; nay, whether the Man himſelf underſtood what he would be at. One while he will have it to be nothing elſe but the Fleſh and Blood of Chriſt; and another while to be a Figure, and the Fleſh and Blood of Chriſt Myſtically. Now he ſays, that Chriſt's Body is <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated</hi> in the Sacrament, than that it is made of the Subſtance of Bread, and by and by, that the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is Celebrated in the Subſtance of Bread and Wine. Sometime he tells us, that 'tis the very Body which Chriſt took of the Virgin; and preſently that it is wholly a Spiritual and Divine thing which we Eat of, and that 'tis his <hi>Spiritual</hi> Fleſh. In one fit he ſays 'tis the Fleſh of Chriſt which repairs and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes <hi>our</hi> Fleſh, becauſe the whole Man is redeemed; and in another he ſays as poſitively, that all muſt be <hi>ſpiritually</hi> underſtood, that we muſt not think of any thing here that is Carnal, and that if there were a real change of the Bread into Fleſh, it would be no more the Fleſh of Chriſt, than now it is, becauſe the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97031:11"/>
whole Myſtery is <hi>Spiritual.</hi> Throughout the whole book there are ſo many looſe, uncouth, and inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent Notions, that there is hardly any thing plain in it but this, that he owns a <hi>Real</hi> preſence, though the Man ſeems miſerably <hi>confounded</hi> how to make you in any meaſure to underſtand it, or how to underſtand himſelf his own meaning.</p>
            <p>As I was reading the Book, I was apt to believe, that either he harped upon that Notion of Chriſt's <hi>Spiritual</hi> Body and Blood in the Sacrament, which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of the Ancient Fathers inſiſted on, and which is of ſuch great uſe for the unfolding of this myſtery; or elſe that his conceits were meerly the raw iſſue of an unripened Judgment (for he Wrote that piece while he was yet a Monk.) But comparing it with his Epiſtle to <hi>Frudegard,</hi> and his expoſition upon St. <hi>Matthew</hi> 26. v. 26. (both which he wrote when he was now Abbot and an <hi>Old</hi> Man) I thought it more reaſonable to conjecture, that as at firſt he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected ſingularity, ſo to the laſt he was reſolved to <hi>perſiſt</hi> in it. For he ſtifly held it, that <hi>the very Body of Chriſt wherein he Suffer'd and Roſe again, is of a Truth in the Sacrament materially and in the propriety of its Nature.</hi> And yet to do him right, I do not ſee that he believ'd the Nature of Bread to be <hi>Annihilated,</hi> or <hi>Tranſubſtantiated,</hi> no, his opinion ſeems quite <hi>diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent</hi> from that. He comes nearer to the Doctrine of <hi>Conſubſtantiation,</hi> that it is true <hi>Bread</hi> and true <hi>Fleſh</hi> too; or rather to the conceit of <hi>Impanation</hi> (as they call it) as if Chriſt <hi>aſſumed the Bread, and united it Corporally to himſelf upon the Conſecration, as he aſſumed our Fleſh, and united it to the Divinity at his Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> But this is a Candid interpretation. Whatever his fancy was, it ſoon ſtartled many <hi>Learned</hi> and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97031:11"/>
               <hi>Great Men</hi> in the Church. For <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> himſelf doth confeſs, <hi>that many doubted of of the Truth of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that many queſtioned, how the Sacrament could be the Body and Blood of Chriſt, and yet Chriſt remain en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire; that he had provoked many to look narrowly into the thing, becauſe it is ſaid, the Fleſh profiteth nothing;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ep ad</hi> Fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>degard. <hi>&amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſ. in</hi> Matth.</note> 
               <hi>that others underſtood it to be not true Fleſh, and true Blood, but only the Vertue of Chriſt's Body and Blood in the Sacrament;</hi> that ſome <hi>reprehended him for what he had written in his Book of the Sacrament, believing that it was not true, and ſuſpecting that his deſign was to be in the head of a Faction; and then with ſome cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler he calls them Prating and Unlearned Men, that would not believe, but that a Body muſt be palpable and viſible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>hard</hi> words were far from ſtifling this matter. <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſius</hi> his New Opinion had taken air, and though it fell vaſtly <hi>ſhort</hi> of Tranſubſtantiation, yet there was enough in it to ſtirr the the zeal of the <hi>Orthodox;</hi> and ſo it was ventilated, till by degrees it brake out into a <hi>flaming</hi> Controverſie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> his Contemporary <hi>Rabanus</hi> was one of the moſt <hi>Eminent</hi> Men of that time; firſt a Monk at <hi>Fuld</hi> in <hi>Franconia,</hi> where afterward he ſucceeded his Friend <hi>Egilo</hi> in the Abbacy, <hi>Anno</hi> 822. and at laſt was Archbiſhop of <hi>Mentz:</hi> The <hi>Glory of</hi> Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and admirably skill'd in all ſorts of Learning, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in the Hebrew, Greek and Latin Languages, as the Romaniſts themſelves do confeſs. As ſoon as <hi>Paſchaſius's</hi> Book came abroad and made a noiſe in the World, this <hi>Rabanus</hi> undertook and confuted it, in an Epiſtle directed to <hi>Egilo</hi> then Abbot of the Monaſtery at <hi>Fuld.</hi> Indeed this Epiſtle is not now extant (care enough has been taken by ſome,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97031:12"/>
who thought themſelves concern'd to <hi>ſuppreſs</hi> it:) But that ſuch an Epiſtle was Written by <hi>Rabanus</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> undeniably appears from ſeveral Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſcripts of an Author of the ſame Age, and a Friend to <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> his Opinion. Three of theſe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſcripts were ſeen by the Learned <hi>Albertinus</hi> in ſome Libraries in <hi>France;</hi> and a Fourth is in the <hi>Cottonian</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Albert <hi>de Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char.</hi> lib. 3. pag. 921. <hi>Uſher.</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the Challenge, p. 17. <hi>&amp; de ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſ. &amp; ſtata</hi> p. 38, 39.</note> Library, and a Fifth at <hi>Sidney</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cambridge;</hi> both which were peruſed by the incomparable Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Uſher.</hi> This Author I ſay, having laid down <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> his Opinion, <hi>that the Fleſh which is received at the Altar, is no other than that which was born of the Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>ſuffer'd on the Croſs, Roſe again from the Grave, and as yet is daily offer'd for the Life of the World; at laſt</hi> he ſays, contra quem <hi>(ſc. Paſcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſium)</hi> ſatis argumentatur &amp; <hi>Rabanus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>againſt</hi> Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſius <hi>both</hi> Rabanus <hi>in his Epiſtle to Abbot</hi> Egilo, <hi>and one</hi> Ratrannus <hi>in a Book written to King</hi> Charles (of <hi>France) argue largely,</hi> ſaying, <hi>that it is another kind of Fleſh.</hi> And beſides <hi>Rabanus</hi> himſelf tells us, that he wrote againſt this Errour of <hi>Paſchaſius</hi>'s in an Epiſtle to Abbot <hi>Egilo.</hi> For in his Penitential ſet out at <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gloſtad</hi> by <hi>Peter Steuart,</hi> he ſays (repeating the very words of <hi>Paſchaſius) ſome of late, not having a Right opinion of the Sacrament of the Lords Body and Blood, have af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Raban peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tential. <hi>c. 33.</hi> de Euchar. ad <hi>Heribald.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that 'tis that very Body and Blood of the Lord, which was born of the Virgin Mary, and in which the Lord ſuffer'd on the Croſs, and roſe again from the Grave: Againſt which Errour</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>we have imployed our laſt endeavours, writing to Abbot</hi> Egilo, <hi>declaring what is truly to be believed concerning Chriſts Body.</hi> It ſeems there was a little <hi>Daſh,</hi> or <hi>raſure</hi> in this paſſage of <hi>Rabanus,</hi> ſuppoſed to have been made by the Monks at <hi>Heingart,</hi> where the Manuſcript was found, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97031:12"/>
'tis an Artifice which has been commonly uſed by many diſingenuous Romaniſts, and a very great Honour it is to their Cauſe, to mutilate and corrupt writings which make againſt them; but 'tis ſufficient for me to note, how <hi>Rabanus</hi> calls the conceit of a Corporal preſence, <hi>a late Errour;</hi> and yet then it was not ſo bulky, as in later Ages, when it ſwell'd into the moſt groſs Opinion of Tranſubſtantiation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 837. or thereabout, a great Council was held at <hi>Cariſiacum</hi> in <hi>France;</hi> the ſame Council, if I mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake <note place="margin">Vide Uſſer <hi>Hiſtor.</hi> Gotteſ. Chalch. p. 87.</note> not, where the Opinions of <hi>Gotteſchalchus</hi> touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Predeſtination were conſider'd and condemn'd, and <hi>Paſchaſius Ratbertus,</hi> then Abbot of <hi>Corbey,</hi> was one of that Council. Whether they determin'd any thing againſt <hi>Paſchaſius himſelf,</hi> is not certain; for the Printed Account we have hitherto had of that Council is very imperfect, but the Learned and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitive <hi>Du Pleſſis</hi> ſaw ſome Manuſcript Acts of this Council, which though they ſtruck immediately at <hi>Amalarius</hi> for ſome Errours he held about the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De miſſa.</hi> lib. 4. cap. 8. pag. 743.</note> yet are they ſo <hi>Oppoſite to Paſchaſius</hi>'s Fancy and <hi>Deſtructive</hi> of it, as if the Council had intended to wound <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> through <hi>Amalarius</hi> his <hi>ſide.</hi> Thus it was: <hi>Amalarius,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Lyons,</hi> was a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable men in that Age; but in ſome points he held very abſurd and monſtrous Opinions; for which rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the Church of <hi>Lyons</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards took it ill, that <hi>Amalari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Multum moleſtè &amp; dolenter accepimus, ut Eccleſiaſtici &amp; prudentes viri tantam injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ſibimetipfis fecerint, ut</hi> Amalarium <hi>de Fedei ratione conſulerent, qui &amp; verbit, &amp; Libris ſuis mendaciis, &amp; erroribus &amp; fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticis, atque hereticis diſputationibus plenis omnes pene apud</hi> Frauciam <hi>Eccleſias, &amp; non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nullas etiam aliarum regiontum quantum in ſe fult infecit atque corrupit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> Lug. dunenſ. <hi>de tribut Epiſtolis;</hi> Bibliothec. P 9.</note> had been conſulted in the cauſe againſt <hi>Gotteſchalchus,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>he had done his endeavour to infect and corrupt all the (hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in</hi> France, <hi>With Lyes and Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and with fantaſtical and He
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97031:13"/>
retical diſputations, that his Writings ought to have been burnt.</hi> The Errours thus objected againſt him ſeem plainly to have been thoſe concerning the Sacrament. For this was one of his <hi>Fantaſtical and Heretical</hi> Notions; that Chriſt hath <hi>a Tripartite Body; one that he took of the Virgin; another that is in us who live upon the Earth; and a Third that is in thoſe who are dead.</hi> This monſtrous Opinion we find in the <hi>35th.</hi> Chapter of his Third Book <hi>de Officiis Eccleſiaſticis;</hi> and it was laid to his charge by the <hi>Cariſiac</hi> Synod, as <hi>Du Pleſſis</hi> ſhews: And this ſeems to be <hi>that foolery about the Tripartite Redy of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ad ultimum quoeſo ne ſequaris ineptias de Tripartito Chriſti Corpore. <hi>Paſchaſ.</hi> ad <hi>Frudegard.</hi> in fine.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which <hi>Paſchaſius him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> caution'd <hi>Frudegard</hi> againſt. For this was a <hi>different</hi> thing from <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> his Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination of the threefold Body of Chriſt. Though <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malarius</hi> favour'd <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> his Opinion as to the <hi>main</hi> of it, yet in ſome things they were divided, that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation being as yet <hi>Raw</hi> and <hi>Undigeſted.</hi> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this, <hi>Amalarius</hi> had another New conceit agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to that of <hi>Paſchaſius, that the ſimple Nature of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Amalar. <hi>de Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic. Eccleſiaſt.</hi> c. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Bread and Wine is turn'd into a reaſonable Nature, that is the Nature of Chriſt's Body and Blood;</hi> though he could not tell what becomes of this Body when 'tis <hi>received,</hi> whether it goes up to <hi>Heaven,</hi> or flies out into the <hi>Air,</hi> or remains in the Communicants <hi>Body</hi> till death, or goes out at the opening of the Vein. Such phantaſtical and heretical conceits had this Man <note place="margin">Anſwer to the Jeſuites Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge <hi>pag.</hi> 79.</note> about this matter; for Biſhop <hi>Uſher</hi> ſaw in <hi>Bennet's Colledge</hi> Library one of his Epiſtles in Manuſcript to <hi>Guitard</hi> wherein he expreſt himſelf to this purpoſe; and the ſame Errours were charged upon him by the <hi>Cariſiac</hi> Synod alſo. Now the Councils definition up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this ſtrikes at all in <hi>ſhort,</hi> to the ruin of <hi>Amalarius</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:97031:13"/>
and <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> his cauſe too; viz. <hi>That the Bread and Wine is Spiritually made the Body of Christ, that is, the Myſtery of our Life and Salvation, wherein one thing is ſeen by the Eye of the Body, and another by the Eye of Faith; that it is the Food of the mind, not of the Belly, that in that viſible Bread and Drink a Man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives the virtue of inviſible Grace, and that the Body of Chriſt is not in the viſible thing, but in the Spiritual Virtue,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Acts of this Council were written by <hi>Florus,</hi> and dedicated to ſeveral Biſhops, and other Great Men at that time: Which is a clear Argument, that the ſenſe of the <hi>Cariſiac</hi> Synod was very agreeable to the received Doctrine of the Church then: Which I note the rather, becauſe for the ſpace of about 200. years no Council but this took any notice (that I know) of the Doctrine of the <hi>Sacrament;</hi> and yet a great many Synods were held on ſeveral occaſions in that long tract of time; and a Controverſie upon ſuch a weighty point could not have eſcaped them all, and this being the firſt that ruin'd the pretence of a Corporal Preſence, it is eaſie to believe, that till now there had been no occaſion for a publick difini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this point; and that when this occaſion was offer'd, they were reſolved to ſtifle this <hi>Innovation</hi> upon its firſt appearance.</p>
            <p>To go on now with matter of Fact: Of thoſe that <hi>ſingly</hi> engaged in the quarrel with <hi>Paſchaſius, Bertram</hi> was the next. You find by the Nameleſs Author a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove mentioned, that not only <hi>Rabanus</hi> wrote againſt him, but alſo <hi>Ratranus,</hi> who is now uſually called <hi>Bertram</hi> (for he is indifferently called <hi>Bertramus, Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tramnus, Ratrannus.)</hi> Whatever his right Name was, he was a Monk of <hi>Corbey,</hi> and a very Eminent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97031:14"/>
about <hi>Anno</hi> 840. for the Controverſie now grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>hot,</hi> eſpecially in <hi>France</hi> where it had been kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and <hi>Carolus Calvus</hi> being very deſirous to quench it in time, directed <hi>Bertram</hi> (ſo I will now call him) to give his ſenſe of it. <hi>Bertram</hi> in obedience to the King's Command wrote an Excellent book upon the Subject; in the beginning whereof he takes notice of <hi>no ſmall Schiſm that then was in the Church,</hi> about the Myſtery of Chriſt's Body and Blood; and then he ſtates the Two Great Queſtions which <hi>Carolus Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus</hi> had propoſed to him.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Whether the Sacrament be a <hi>Figure</hi> of ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret thing which is exhibited with it, and which is the Object not of Senſe, but of Faith.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Whether that thing ſo exhibited be the very <hi>Natural</hi> Body of Chriſt, which was Born of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary,</hi> which Suffer'd, which was Dead and Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, which Roſe again, which Aſcended into Heaven, and Sitteth at the Right Hand of the Father (which was the Opinion, and the very words of <hi>Paſcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius?)</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. As to the Firſt, though (at the cloſe of his Book) he denies the Sacrament to be a <hi>meer Figure,</hi> a bare Shadow, an empty Sign without Chriſt's real Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; yet he owns it to be a Figure; and ſolidly proves from Scripture, Reaſon and the Authority of ſeveral Ancient Fathers, that it is a Figure, and that under the viſible and corruptible Elements, as under a Cover, is contained <hi>a Divine and Spiritual Thing,</hi> which is believed to be there upon Conſecration through the Operation of the Spirit, <hi>without any Corporal change of the things we ſee, but the Elements</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Neque iſta commutatio cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poraliter, ſed ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualiter facta. Quoniam ſub ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamento Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rei panis, Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rei<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vini ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituale Corpus Chriſti, ſpiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſanguis exiſtit. Nam ſecundum Creaturarum Subſtantiam, quod fuerunt ante Conſecratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, hoc &amp; poſten conſiſtunt.</note>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:97031:14"/>
               <hi>remaining ſtill Corporeal Bread, and Corporeal Wine.</hi> For as to that he is poſitive, <hi>that in reſpect of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of thoſe Creatures, they continue the very ſame thing which they were before Conſecration:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. And as to the Second Queſtion, he diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes with St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> and St. <hi>Jerome,</hi> between the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural</hi> and the <hi>Spiritual</hi> Body of Chriſt, and peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily determines againſt <hi>Paſchaſius,</hi> and that over and over, that it is not the true, proper, and Natural Body, which was born of the Virgin, which Suffer'd and was Dead, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which is receiv'd in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, but his <hi>Spiritual Body;</hi> that 'tis Chriſt's Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, though not his <hi>Corporal,</hi> but <hi>Spiritual</hi> Body; that 'tis the Blood of Chriſt, though not his <hi>Corporal,</hi> but <hi>Spiritual</hi> Blood: Which he explains thus, not that Chriſt hath two Bodies ſeverally exiſtent, and utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly different from each other in Nature, as Body and Spirit are; but becauſe <hi>a Spiritual power and efficacy</hi> goes along with the bodily Bread and Wine; becauſe by and with theſe Creatures, there is Miniſtred to the Faithful <hi>a Vital Virtue, the vigour of a Spiritual Life, that word of God which is the living Bread, a Divine Virtue which ſecretly diſpenſeth Salvation to all Faithful Receivers, an inviſible Power, which ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally miniſtreth the Subſtance of Eternal Life, a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Spiritual Operation, of inviſible efficacy, and of Divine Virtue</hi> (as <hi>Bertram</hi> often expreſſeth himſelf) all which is ſuppoſed to be derived from Chriſt's Glorified Humanity, and therefore not improperly call'd his Spiritual Body, according to that Old Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which St. <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>A'exandria,</hi> and the <hi>Epheſine</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:97031:15"/>
Council had of the viviſick power of Chriſt's Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as being repleniſht with the Deity.</p>
            <p>But I will not give you a large account of this Book, becauſe it is common, and becauſe every one knows how ſtrongly it confutes the Opinion not only of Tranſubſtantiation, but alſo of a <hi>Corporal preſence,</hi> which was the New phancy of <hi>Paſchaſius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall only obſerve this to you by the way, that the bleſſed Maſters of the <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> whoſe buſineſs it was to ſearch into Books, and to let Men know what Authors they were not to uſe (for the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Catholick Faith cannot well endure Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) that they might be luſtily reveng'd upon poor <hi>Bertram</hi> for his plain dealing, ordered this invaluable Piece of his to be <hi>ſuppreſt,</hi> and accordingly 'tis ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked among the Prohibited Books in the <hi>Tridentine, Roman</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh Indices Expargatorii.</hi> Only the Men of <hi>Doway,</hi> miſtruſting that this courſe would turn to the ſhame and prejudice of their Cauſe, the Book being abroad in all Mens hands, thought it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to Tolerate it with ſome <hi>Blottings, Alterations, and Conſtructions of their own making. Whereas</hi> (ſay they) <hi>there are very many Errours in other Old Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Writers, which we bear with, extenuate, excuſe, many times deny by ſome Artificial device or other, and fix a commodious ſenſe upon them; we ſee not but</hi> Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tram <note place="margin">ſudex Belgic.</note> 
               <hi>(a Catholick Presbyter) may deſerve the ſame E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and diligent Riviſal.</hi> But with what Equity they have uſed him, or rather how baſely and barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly they have wronged him, any man may ſee, that will but look into the <hi>Belgick Index Expurgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius;</hi> for here they have quite <hi>raſed</hi> him, there they have <hi>wreſted</hi> him, there again they have made him ſpeak flat <hi>Contradictions,</hi> throughout they have uſed
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97031:15"/>
ſo many <hi>Charms</hi> and <hi>Spells</hi> over him, as if they had perfectely deſigned by hook or by crook even to Tranſubſtantiate Old <hi>Bertram</hi> out of <hi>himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But theſe Great Men ſtood not <hi>alone</hi> in this quarrel. <hi>Bertram</hi>'s contemporary, the famous <hi>Joannes Scotus E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigena</hi> was deeply concern'd in it too. I give him that Character, becauſe the Hiſtorians which ſpeak of him mention him with Honour. <hi>Carolus Calvus</hi> of <hi>France</hi> had ſuch a value for him, that he made <note place="margin">Hovedan. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</hi>
               </note> him his Companion at Bed and Board, Pope <hi>Nicolas</hi> himſelf gave him the Character of a Man renowned for his great knowledge: Nor was it any thing but his Eminent worth that made King <hi>Alfred,</hi> that Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of Learning, invite him back into <hi>England;</hi> and fix him in the Monaſtery at <hi>Malmesbury,</hi> for the advancement of good Literature. Briefly, thoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations of his, which, while he was yet in <hi>France,</hi> he wrote againſt <hi>Gotteſchalchus,</hi> and which did ſo trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the whole Church of <hi>Lyons</hi> how to Anſwer, are a ſufficient Argument of his Abilities Now all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, that this <hi>Joannes Scotus Erigena</hi> went hand in hand with <hi>Bertram,</hi> as to the Doctrine of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, inſomuch that ſome would make us believe, that the Book commonly aſcribed to <hi>Bertram</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by this <hi>Scotus.</hi> And though I ſee no good Reaſons to think ſo, yet certain it is, that he wrote a <hi>Tract</hi> upon the ſame Subject, and to the ſame effect, and very probably at the Command of <hi>Carolus Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus</hi> alſo. About two hundred years after, when <hi>Berengarius</hi> his buſineſs grew hot, and the Opinion of a Corporal Preſence by the intereſt of a Faction had gotten ground, <hi>Scotus</hi> his Book was urged and <hi>Vindicated</hi> by <hi>Berengarius;</hi> and his adverſary <hi>Lanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>franck</hi> own'd, that 'twas written in <hi>Oppoſition</hi> to <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſius;</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:97031:16"/>
for which Reaſon it was condemn'd by that partial Synod at <hi>Vercellis Anno</hi> 1050. By the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count we have of it now, it appears, that <hi>Scotus</hi> fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly went, as <hi>Bertram</hi> did upon the ſenſe of St. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe, Jerome, Auſtin</hi> and other of the Ancients. And this is very obſervable, that in the Controverſie with <hi>Gotteſchalchus</hi> about Predeſtination which was ardent at that time, theſe two Learned Men were <hi>divided;</hi> for <hi>Bertram</hi> was on <hi>Gotteſchalchus</hi> his <hi>ſide,</hi> and <hi>Scotus</hi> was <hi>againſt</hi> him: But however they differ'd in <hi>that</hi> Point, in <hi>this</hi> concerning the Sacrament they were both agreed, which ſhews, that it was not Friendſhip, or Prejudice, or the love of a party which Govern'd them in their perſwaſions, but the entire love they had for thoſe things which ſeem'd to be True; and that it appear'd to them both as an unqueſtionable Truth, from Scripture, Reaſon, and the Catholick Doctrine of the Ancient Church (which they both inſiſted on) that Chriſt's Preſence in the Sacrament is only <hi>Spiritual.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I end this with an Obſervation of a moderate Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yet living in the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church, concerning this <hi>Scotus;</hi> that if he had advanced any New Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, he would certainly have been reproved for it <note place="margin">Treatiſe of Tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation turn'd into Engliſh, and Printed at <hi>London.</hi> 1687. <hi>pag.</hi> 58.</note> by the Church of <hi>Eyons,</hi> by <hi>Prudentius,</hi> by <hi>Florus,</hi> by the Colineils of <hi>Valence</hi> and <hi>Langres,</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned and cenſur'd his opinions on the Doctrine of Predeſtination.</p>
            <p>As for his <hi>Death;</hi> though he wsa barbarouſly Murder'd by his own Scholars at <hi>Malmesbury,</hi> it is ſo far from being a Blot upon his Memory, or a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement to his Cauſe, that it is an Honour to <hi>Both:</hi> For every one knows, he was reckon'd a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr. Indeed it is not certain what the true occaſion
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97031:16"/>
of that horrid wickedneſs was. Very probably he had been too liberal of his Wit againſt the dull and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Monks: Though <hi>Genebrard</hi> inſinuates, that it was for his Doctrine of the Sacrament, yet Monſieur <hi>Duval</hi> conſeſſeth, this was <hi>Genebrards private conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, not founded on any Authority or Teſtimony.</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, <note place="margin">Genebrard. <hi>in Liturg Dionyſ.</hi> Duval <hi>annot. in</hi> lib. <hi>Eccleſiae</hi> Lugd. <hi>adv.</hi> Scot.</note> the conceit of a Corporal Preſence was hardly ſo much as known at that time in <hi>England;</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it came to be vended here? it was a long time e're it came to that value, as to be made the <hi>price of Blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There were many other men of note in this Ninth Century, whom divers Writers on our ſide have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to have declared their minds againſt the Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Paſchaſius;</hi> ſuch as <hi>Hincmarus, Waleſridus Strabo, Heribald, Druſilmanus,</hi> and ſeveral more, whoſe names you meet with in many Latin Tracts, and in that Engliſh Treatiſe I mention'd juſt now. But I will not ſpend my time upon every little quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, leaſt I ſhould make this Letter ſwell beyond a due proportion; and beſides I think it not amiſs to divert you a little with ſome account of the poſture of this affair about that time here at <hi>home,</hi> becauſe I have juſt ſpoken of <hi>Scotus,</hi> who was either our <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Man,</hi> or a near <hi>Neighbour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Somewhat after the <hi>900th.</hi> year from Chriſt, <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do</hi> was ArchBiſhop of <hi>Canterbury;</hi> and he would have brought into <hi>England</hi> the belief of a Corporal preſence: But it ſeems the Clergy were too <hi>Honeſt</hi> to be wrought upon. <hi>In thoſe days moſt doubted of the Truth</hi> (meaning, the Subſtantial Preſence) <hi>of Chriſt's Body in the Sacrament,</hi> ſaith <hi>William</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Malmesb. <hi>de geſt. pontif.</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gl. p. 201. Osbern. <hi>in vita</hi> Odon.</note> of <hi>Malmesbury:</hi> Some <hi>Clergy Men aſſerted</hi> (ſaith <hi>Osbern) that the Bread and Wine after Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97031:17"/>
remain in their own former Subſtance.</hi> He ſaith, <hi>ſome,</hi> but he ſhould have ſaid the <hi>Generality of</hi> Men believed ſo, for it was then the <hi>common</hi> Opinion in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> But this has been the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of that ſort of men, when they are to tell Noſes, or go to the Poll, to repreſent the adverſe party as a little <hi>Handful,</hi> though ſometimes to their coſt they find themſelves ſadly <hi>miſtaken</hi> in their account.</p>
            <p>For after the death of <hi>Odo,</hi> this was the common Faith of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> even in the days of <hi>Elfrick</hi> (or <hi>Alfrick)</hi> who was made Abbot of <hi>Malmesbury</hi> by King <hi>Edgar Anno</hi> 974. if <hi>Ingulphus</hi> be right in his computation. <hi>Indeed about</hi> that time Men did <hi>ſearch, how bread that is gather'd of Corn, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">A <hi>Saxon</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily on Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-Day.</note> 
               <hi>through fires heat baked, may be turned to Chriſt's Body,</hi> &amp;c. But the Doctrine of our Church which was then <hi>profeſt,</hi> and which upon that ſearch was the more vigorouſly <hi>maintain'd,</hi> was, that 'tis Chriſt's Body <hi>Mystically, Spiritually,</hi> and by <hi>ſignification.</hi> The Reaſon why I ſay it, is this. <hi>Elfrick</hi> was of ſuch great eſteem in the Church, that his Writings were ſorted among the <hi>publick Acts</hi> of the Church, and judged to contain the avowed and Authentick Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> then: For ſome of them were put among the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Canons and Conſtitutions</hi> for the inſtruction and good Government of the <hi>Clergy;</hi> and ſome of his Writings were publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>read,</hi> in Churches, as Authoriz'd Homilies for the Information of all People. This account I find in in the Preface to a very ſcarce Book, under this Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, <hi>A Teſtimony of Antiquity, ſhewing the Ancient Faith of the Church of</hi> England <hi>touching the Sacrament of the Body and Blood of the Lord here publickly preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and alſo received in the</hi> Saxon <hi>time.</hi> This Book
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97031:17"/>
was Printed in Archbiſhop <hi>Parkers</hi> days (but there is no printed date of the year, only in MSS. 1567.) and Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> ſeems to have taken out of it all that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count which he gives us of this matter in his <hi>Acts and Monuments.</hi> It is a little <hi>Manual</hi> of ſome of <hi>Elfrick's</hi> Works: Firſt a <hi>Sermon</hi> Tranſlated by <hi>Elfrick</hi> out of ſome Latin Author into the <hi>Saxon</hi> Language (which was publickly read here on Eaſter-Day) and then two of his Epiſtles to two Biſhops: <hi>Out of which,</hi> ſaith the Prefacer, <hi>it is not hard to know, not only ſo much what</hi> Alfrickes <hi>judgment was in this Controverſie, but alſo, that more is, what was the common received Doctrine herein of the whole Church of</hi> England <hi>as well when</hi> El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fricke <hi>himſelf lived, as before his time, and alſo after his time, even from him to the Conqueſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The piece I now ſpeak of being a Rarity, I will give you this account of it, premiſing this only, that by <hi>Houſel</hi> is meant the Elements in the Sacrament, the Sacramental Bread and Wine. In the Sermon for Eaſter (the <hi>Saxon</hi> Language on the one Page, and the common Engliſh over againſt it on the other) after a pretty long compariſon made in the beginning between the <hi>Paſchal</hi> Lamb in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour, theſe words follow: <q>Now Men have often ſearched, and do yet often ſearch, how Bread that is gathered of Corne, and through fyers heate baked may be turned to Chriſtes Body, or how Wyne that is preſſed out of many Grapes, is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned through one bleſſing to the Lords Bloude. Now ſay we to ſuche men, that ſome thinges be ſpoken of Chriſt by ſignification, ſome thyngs by thyng certain. True thyng is and certain, that Chriſt was born of a Maid, and ſuffered Death of his own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, and was buryed, and on thys day roſe from
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97031:18"/>
Death. He is ſayd Bread by a ſignification, and a Lamb, and a Lyon, and a Mountayne. He is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led bread, becauſe he is our Life and Angels Life. He is ſayd to be a Lamb for his innocence; a Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for ſtrength wherewith he overcame the ſtrong Devil. But Chriſt is not ſo notwithſtanding after true Nature, neither Bread, nor a Lamb, nor a Lyon, why is then that holy <hi>Houſel</hi> called Chriſt's Body or his Blood, if it be not truly that it is called? Truly the Bread and the Wyne which by the Maſſe of the Prieſt is Halowed, ſhew one thing without to humayne underſtanding, and another thing they call within to beleving mindes. Without they be ſene Bread and Wine both in Figure and in taſt; and they be truely after their halowing Chriſtes Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and hys bloude through Ghoſtly miſtery. An heathen Childe is Chriſtened, yet he altereth not hys ſhape without though he be chaunged within. He is brought to the Font-Stone ſinful through <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> diſobedience: Howbeit he is waſhed from all Sinne within though he hath not altered hys ſhape without. Even ſo the Holy Font Water that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the well ſpryng of Life is lyke in ſhape to other Waters, and is ſubject to corruption; but the Holy Ghoſtes myght commeth to the corruptible Water through the Prieſtes Bleſſing, and it may after waſh the Body and Soule from all Sinne, through Ghoſtly myghte. Beholde now we ſee two thyngs in this one Creature. After true Nature that Water is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible Water, and after Ghoſtly miſtery hath ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing mighte. So alſo if we beholde that Holy <hi>Houſell</hi> after bodely underſtanding, then ſee we that it is a Creature corruptible and mutable: If we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge therein ghoſtly myghte, then underſtand
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97031:18"/>
we that lyfe is therein, and that it giveth immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality to them that eat it with beliefe. Muche is betwixt the inviſible myght of the Holy Houſell, and the viſible ſhape of its proper Nature. It is naturally corruptible Bread, and corruptible Wyne, and is by myght of Gods worde truely Chriſtes Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and his Bloude. Much is betwixt the Body Chriſt ſuffered in, and the Body that is Halowed to Houſell. The Body truely that Chriſt ſuffred in, was born of the Fleſh of <hi>Mary,</hi> with bloude and with bone, with Skinne and with Sinews, in Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Limmes, with a reaſonable Soule living: And his Ghoſtly Body; which we call the Houſell, is ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered of many cornes, without Bloude and Bone, without Limme, without Soule, and therefore no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is to be underſtand therein bodelye, but all is Ghoſtly to be underſtand. Whatſoever is in that Houſell which giveth Subſtance of Lyfe, that is of the Ghoſtly myghte, and inviſible doing. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is the Holy Houſell called a miſterye, becauſe there is one thing in it ſeene, and another thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanded. That which is there ſene hath bodily ſhape, and that we do there underſtand, hath Ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly might. Certainly Chriſt's body which ſuffred Death and roſe from Death, never dyeth henceforth; but is Eternal and unpaſſible: That Houſell is Temporal, not Eternall; corruptible, and dealed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſondrye parts; Chewed between Teeth, and ſent into the Belly: Howbeit nevertheleſſe after Ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly myghte, it is all in every parte.—This miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye is a pledge and a Figure; Chriſtes Body is Truth it ſelf. This pledge we do keep miſtically, until that we become to the Truth it ſelf, and then is this Pledge ended. Truely it is ſo as we before have
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97031:19"/>
ſayd, Chriſtes Bodye and hys Bloude; not bodilye, but Ghoſtly.—The Saviour ſayeth, <hi>He that eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth my Fleſh, and Drinketh my Blood, hath everlaſting Life.</hi> And he bad them not eat that Body which he was going about with, nor that bloude to drink which he ſhed for us, but he ment with thoſe wordes that Holy Houſell, which Ghoſtley is hys Body, and hys Bloude; and he that taſteth it with belea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving hart, hath that Eternal Lyfe.—Certainly this Houſell which we do now halow at God's Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, is a remembrance of Chriſtes body which he offred for us, and of his Bloude which he ſhed for us.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The meaning of this Myſtery being there thus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded, the reſt of that Sermon is, touching the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how people ſhould receive it; which I ſhall not tranſcribe, becauſe it is not ſo much to my preſent <note place="margin">In <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the six Articles.</note> purpoſe; and the whole is in Mr. <hi>Fox,</hi> where you may peruſe it at your leiſure.</p>
            <p>The next thing is an Epiſtle of <hi>Elfrick's</hi> to <hi>Wulf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſine,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Scyrburne,</hi> by occaſion of an ill cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome the Prieſts had of keeping the Conſecrated E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements by them an whole year. It is a ſhort one, and you ſhall have it all.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Some Priſtes keepe the Houſell that is conſecrate on Eaſter Day all the yere for Syke Men. But they do greatlye amyſſe, becauſe it waxeth horye and rotten. And theſe will not underſtand how grevous penaunce the paenitential Booke teacheth by thys, if the Houſell become horye and rotten; or yf that it be loſt; or be eaten of Beaſts by negly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence. Men ſhall reſerve more carefullye that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Houſell, and not reſerve it to long, but Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate other of newe for Syke men alwayes within
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:97031:19"/>
a weke or a fortnight that it be not ſo much as horye. For ſo holy is the Houſell which to day is halowed as that which on Eaſter-day was hallowed. That Holy Houſell is Chriſtes Body, not bodily but Ghoſtly. Not the bodye which he ſuffred in, but the Body of which he ſpake, when he bleſſed Bread and Wyne to Houſell a night before his ſuffring, and ſaid by the Bleſſed Bread, thys is my Body, and agayne by the Holy Wyne, this is my bloude which is ſhed for many in forgiveneſs of Sinnes. Underſtand now that the Lord who could turn that Bread before his ſuffring to his Body, and the Wyne to his Bloude Ghoſtlye, that the ſelfe ſame Lorde bleſſeth dayly through the Prieſtes handes Bread and Wyne to hys Ghoſtlye bodye, and to his Ghoſtlye bloude.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The other Epiſtle is to <hi>Wulfſtane</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Yorke,</hi> to the ſame purpoſe with the former, only ſomewhat longer; and about the middle of it he ſaith, <q>Chriſt Haloweth dayly by the handes of the Prieſt Bread to hys Body, and Wyne to his bloud in Ghoſtly miſtery, as we read in bokes, And yet that lively bread is not ſo notwithſtanding, not the ſelfe ſame Body that Chriſt ſuffered in. Nor that Holy Wyne is the Saviours Bloud which was ſhed for us in bodely thing, but in Ghoſtly underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Both be truely that bread hys Body, and that Wyne alſo hys bloud, as was the Heavenly Bread, which we call Manna, that fed forty yeres God's people.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This Epiſtle to <hi>Wulfſtane</hi> was firſt Written by <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fricke</hi> in Latin, and then by <hi>Wulfſtanes</hi> directions Tranſlated by him into Engliſh, though not Word for Word, as <hi>Elfrick</hi> tells him. And the Words ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:97031:20"/>
in the Latin are theſe: <q>Intelligite modo ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotes, quod ille Dominus qui ante paſſionem ſuam potuit convertere illum panem, &amp; illud Vinum ad ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Corpus &amp; ſanguinem; ipſe quotidie ſanctificat per manus Sacerdotum ſuorum Panem ad ſuum Corpus ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualiter, &amp; Vinum ad ſuum Sanguinem (non fit tamen hoc Sacrificium Corpus ejus in quo paſſus eſt pro nobis; nec Sanguis ejus, quem pro nobis effundit: Sed ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliter Corpus ejus efficitur &amp; ſanguis; ſicut Manna quod de Coelo pluit, &amp; aqua quoe de Petra Fluxit)</q>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, Theſe Three Things of <hi>Elfrick</hi>'s are a Noble Monument of the Faith of the Church of <hi>England</hi> even to the Tenth Century: And though we find them in Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> and ſome other Authors, yet I thought my ſelf obliged to give you this ſhort ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of them out of a little Manual (which a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Friend of mine hath lent me) becauſe at the end of it there <hi>is an atteſtation in</hi> Manuſcript ſigned by Seventeen Biſhops of our Church, under their own hands (as it ſeems) that the Engliſh Tranſlation of this Sermon and the two Epiſtles is exactly agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the <hi>Saxon</hi> Copies, which upon the Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were found in the Libraries of the Cathedral Churches, <hi>Worceſter, Hereford,</hi> and <hi>Exeter;</hi> from which places (ſaith the Preface) divers of theſe Books have been deliver'd into the hands of the moſt Reverend Father, <hi>Matthew</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> (I ſuppoſe Dr. <hi>Parker)</hi> Leaſt any doubt ſhould ariſe about the Tranſlation, whether it were skillfully or faithfully done; there is (as I told you) at the <hi>End,</hi> this <hi>atteſtation</hi> in <hi>Manuſcript:</hi> 
               <q>Now that this foreſaid <hi>Saxon</hi> Homily with the other <hi>Teſtimonies before alledged</hi> do fully agree <hi>to</hi> the Old Ancient Books (whereof ſome be written in the Old Saxon, and ſome in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine)
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:97031:20"/>
from whence they are taken. Theſe here under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written upon diligent peruſing and comparing the ſame, have found by conference that they are truly put forth in Print without any adding, or withdrawing any thing, for the more faithful reporting of the ſame. In Witneſs whereof they have ſubſcribed their</q> Names (I will not go about to imitate their ſeveral dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent hands leaſt I prove a Bungler at it; but I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, the Biſhop of <hi>Durham's</hi> Title is very differently Written from all the reſt; for it is in Greek Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters)</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Matthue <hi>Archbiſhop of</hi> Canterburye.</item>
               <item>2 Tho. Ebor. Archiepiſcopus.</item>
               <item>3 Edm. London.</item>
               <item>4 Ja. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>5 Rob. Winton.</item>
               <item>6 William <hi>Buſhoppe of</hi> Chiceſter.</item>
               <item>7 Jo. <hi>Buſhop of</hi> Heref.</item>
               <item>8 Richarde <hi>Biſhope of</hi> Ely.</item>
               <item>9 Ed. Wigorn.</item>
               <item>10 N. Lincoln.</item>
               <item>11 R. Meneven.</item>
               <item>12 Thomas Covent <hi>and</hi> Lich.</item>
               <item>13 John Norwic.</item>
               <item>14 Joannes Carleolen.</item>
               <item>15 Will. Ceſtren.</item>
               <item>16 Thomas Aſſaphen.</item>
               <item>17 Nicolaus Bangor.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Hii Patres precedentes ſubſcripſerunt manibus ſuis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priis in hoc Libello.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now out of the whole four things are obſervable. 1. That even before the time of <hi>Elfrick,</hi> the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:97031:21"/>
of Chriſts Spiritual preſence only, was the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine commonly and currently received in all the Weſtern Churches, whatever fantaſtical Notions ſome private men might entertain to the contrary. For thoſe Eighty Sermons which <hi>Elfrick</hi> ſpake of, as of his <note place="margin">Preface to the Book now mention'd.</note> own Writing (whereof that upon Eaſter-Day was one) were not of his own compoſure, but Tranflati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which he made out of Latin Writers; which <note place="margin">Ib.</note> ſhews, that the Latins whom he followed and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated had been poſitive againſt the new conceit of a Corporal preſence.</p>
            <p>2. That in <hi>Elfrck</hi>'s time the ſame Doctrine was conſtantly held throughout the whole Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> as the True Doctrine. For how can we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that <hi>Elfricks</hi> Tranſlations could be read publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Churches in <hi>England,</hi> if the Engliſh Biſhops did not believe them to contain Doctrines that were found and agreeable to the Catholick Faith? Or how can we conceive, that <hi>Elfrick</hi>'s Epiſtles ſhould be put among the publick Writings of our Church, had not the Doctrines in them been publickly own'd and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt here? And yet it is evident, that among other Canons which our Biſhops collected out of <hi>Gildas,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ib.</note> 
               <hi>Theodorus, Egbert, Alcuine,</hi> and out of the Fathers of the Primitive Ages, they did ſort thoſe Epiſtles of <hi>Elfrick,</hi> for the better ordering of the Engliſh Church.</p>
            <p>3. That thoſe Writings of <hi>Elfrick</hi>'s did ſo dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly ſtrike at the Errours of <hi>Paſchaſius,</hi> as if he had purpoſely deſigned to prevent thoſe Errours from creeping into this Kingdom, and throughly to ſeaſon the whole Nation againſt them. For in ſome places he takes the Opinion, nay the very words of <hi>Paſcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> and contradicts him ſo flatly in the words of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:97031:21"/>
               <hi>Bertram</hi> and others of the former Century, that you would think he had ſome of thoſe Authors before him, as perhaps he had.</p>
            <p>4. That upon the Conqueſt, when divers of the Foreign Clergy came hither with and after <hi>Lancfrank</hi> (an <hi>Italian</hi> Patron of <hi>Paſchaſius</hi>'s groſs Opinion, and now ſent for by the Conqueror to be Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury)</hi> they found the Doctrine of the Spiritual preſence only taught and profeſt in the Church of <hi>England.</hi> For this reaſon they fell ſoul upon the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of our Church; and eſpecially upon thoſe La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Authors which <hi>Elfrick</hi> had made uſe of, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what they could underſtand of <hi>Elfrick</hi>'s own Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings So that thoſe Eighty Latin Sermons, which <hi>Elfrick</hi> had Tranſlated, are long ago loſt; nor did the Latin Epiſtle to <hi>Wulfſtane</hi> (which they found in the Libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and probably was given to that Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> by <hi>Wulfſtane</hi> himſelf) eſcape them neither. For in part of that Epiſtle, where the tender point lay, a perfect <hi>Raſure</hi> was committed: I have Noted the words above in a Parentheſis, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>this Sacrifice is not made that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Non fit tamen hoc Sacrificium Corpus ejus in quo paſſus eſt pro nobis, neque Sanguis ejus quem pro nobis effudit; ſed ſpiritualiter Corpus ejus efficitur &amp; San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis, ſicut Manna quod de Coelo pluit, &amp; aqua quoe de Petra fluxit.</note> 
               <hi>Body of Chriſt in which he ſuffer'd for us, nor that Blood of Chriſt which he ſhed for us, but it becomes Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually his Body and Blood; as the Manna that deſcended from Heaven, and the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which flowed out of the Rock.</hi> Theſe words were flatly and expreſly againſt the Opinion of <hi>Paſchaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us;</hi> and therefore they were quite raſed out; tho' afterwards they were reſtored to us, out of another Latin Copy of the ſame Epiſtle in the Church of <hi>Exeter,</hi> which by good luck had eſcaped their Tallons.</p>
            <p>Had theſe Men underſtood the <hi>Saxon</hi> Language,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97031:22"/>
perhaps we ſhould have had very little or nothing of <hi>Elfricks</hi> Writings left us. But ſuch <hi>foul play</hi> is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident Argument of a very <hi>bad Cauſe:</hi> And ſo I ſhall leave it to your conſideration, what little Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the Romaniſts have to call us Hereticks and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novators in this point, when 'tis ſo plain that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation lieth at their own door, and that when it firſt began to peep into the World, the Church of <hi>England</hi> would not endure it; but even in the days of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> when the Controverſie about it was ſo hot abroad (eſpecially in <hi>France)</hi> She ſtill main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd the Doctrine of the <hi>ſpiritual preſence,</hi> ſo that it held on conſtantly here to the time of the <hi>Conqueſt;</hi> and might have held on ſtill in an uninterrupted courſe from Age to Age, had it not been for ſome <hi>Workers of Iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us now croſs the Sea again, and go on with out Relation of this matter, how it ſtood abroad; whence I have a little diverted you, though I hope with no unuſeful or unpleaſant Digreſſion.</p>
            <p>In the Tenth Century this Controverſie ſeem'd to lie pretty <hi>Quiet;</hi> ſome following the phancy of <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſius,</hi> that Chriſt's Natural Body is in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, his Body properly ſo called, that which he took of the Holy Virgin, that which ſuffer'd upon the Croſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Others following the Catholick Faith of the Ancient Church, that it is Chriſt's <hi>Spiritual Body;</hi> meaning, not his Fleſh <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly,</hi> but the <hi>Virtue</hi> of his Fleſh; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Qui dicunt eſſe virtutem Carnis non Carnem, virtutem Sanguinis non Sangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</hi> Paſchaſ. <hi>in</hi> Math. 26.</note> not his Blood, but the <hi>Virtue</hi> of his Blood, as <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> himſelf re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents their meaning in his time. The Truth is, this Tenth Century abounded with Men from whom
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:97031:22"/>
the World could not expect any thing that was good, ſome very illiterate; ſome very Dull and Unactive; ſome very Lewd; ſome very Ambitious and ſelf en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and ſome quite diſcouraged by the tempeſtuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the times. By the account all Learned Men have given us, it was a moſt <hi>Infamous</hi> Age; the worſt that ever was, or hath been hitherto, ſince the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>Probable it is, that at this time <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion did ſpread, and even to the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> when nothing in compariſon was in the way to ſtop it. And when it was once gotten thither, 'tis ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to believe that <hi>indigent</hi> Men or <hi>flatterers</hi> would be found to <hi>comply</hi> with it. For how can you think that ſuch Men in ſuch an Age would reſiſt the ſtrong Temptations of a Court, and not reſign up Truth and their own Conſciences as a compoſition for their Crimes, or as a price for their Preferments, the Popes having now got ſo much power into their hands? Beſides the Prieſts might eaſily foreſee what a proſitable Errour this would prove in time; what Authority they would hereby gain over people, and how eaſily they might have their Purſes and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences at Command: For what will not Men do, to have the very Body of their Saviour put into their Mouths? And when a Prieſt hath his Penitent at his knee, he muſt needs have full power over him, if he can make him believe that he hath his God in his hand too.</p>
            <p>For theſe and the like Reaſons, the <hi>Paſchaſian</hi> Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Corporal Preſence ſtole about, without meeting with any publick oppoſition in this Age, wherein there was ſuch a great ſcarcity of <hi>Writers,</hi> and a greater of <hi>Scholars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:97031:23"/>
Yet in all this time I do not find any footſteps of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi> That Doctrine was <hi>grafted</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards upon the wild conceit of <hi>Paſchaſius,</hi> to the great miſchief of the World, that hath been poyſon'd ſince with its very unſavoury and deadly <hi>Fruit,</hi> ſomewhat like that which grew upon the <hi>Tree of Knowledge of Good and Evil,</hi> the occaſion of Mans Fall.</p>
            <p>I will not diſſemble with you. The moſt Learned and impartial Men about this time, both before and after the Tenth Century, did ſpeak of the preſence of Chriſts Body in the Sacrament in very high terms. But their Opinon was this; that the conſecrated Bread becomes Chriſts Body, not by a <hi>Substantial change</hi> of the one into the other, nor by an Identity of Nature in <hi>Both</hi> (for they all held the True Body of Chriſt to be ſtill in Heaven, and in Heaven only) But they conceived the Bread and the Body to be <hi>U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited,</hi> by means of a <hi>Third</hi> Thing (that is by the Holy Spirit) whereby the Bread and the Body were <hi>United by a myſticall Conſociation, and by an ineffable Conjunction;</hi> both Bread and Body remaining ſtill <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct</hi> in their own proper <hi>Natures.</hi> I pray obſerve it: They believed (as very many of the Ancient Fathers did) that upon the Prieſts bleſſing, that <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Spirit which repleniſheth, and dwelleth in Chriſt's glorified Body in Heaven, doth alſo repleniſh the Bread and Wine at the Euchariſt; and that by this mediation of the Spirit, the Holy Elements are joyned to Chriſt's Body by a Divine and Spiritual coadunation.</hi> Now this is a quite <hi>different</hi> thing from Tranſubſtantiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for that ſuppoſeth the matter of the Elements to be annihilated, or to paſs into another Subſtance; whereas the Divines of former Ages believ'd no more
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:97031:23"/>
but a Myſtical and Spiritual <hi>Union:</hi> And howſoever they expreſt themſelves about the <hi>Converſion, Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation,</hi> and <hi>Transfuſion</hi> of the Elements, 'tis evident they meant only the <hi>transferring</hi> of them, from a Common to a Sacramental <hi>Uſe,</hi> and the raiſing of them up from the meer condition of Earthly Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to an high degree of Divine Dignity and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence; being now no longer <hi>bare</hi> Bread, and <hi>bare</hi> Wine, but things of a ſublime <hi>Quality</hi> and <hi>Condition,</hi> the venerable Means and Inſtruments of Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating Chriſt's Body and Blood to us, through the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Operation of the Holy Ghoſt. All which is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſiſtent with the Church of <hi>England</hi>'s Notion of Chriſt's <hi>Real Spiritual</hi> Preſence; but is <hi>oppoſite</hi> to the <hi>Paſchaſian</hi> conceit of a groſs <hi>Corporal</hi> Preſence, and utterly Deſtructive of the <hi>later</hi> conceit of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation.</p>
            <p>But to go on. In the beginning of the Eleventh Century, the <hi>Paſchaſian</hi> Doctrine met with freſh Oppoſition. For the Romiſh Writers themſelves confeſs, that <hi>Leuthericus</hi> (who was Archbiſhop of <hi>Sens</hi> in <hi>France, Anno</hi> 1004) was a Great Stickler a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. <hi>Baronius</hi> tells us, that he fell under King <hi>Roberts</hi> diſpleaſure for that Reaſon. The Writer of the Life of Pope <hi>John</hi> the Seventeenth, in one of the Tomes of the Councils, would have it, that <hi>this</hi> Leuthericus <hi>ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hujus tempore <hi>Leuthericus</hi> Senonenſis Archiepiſcopus hoereſis <hi>Berengarianae</hi> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mordia &amp; ſemina ſparſit.</note> 
               <hi>the Seeds of the</hi> Berengarian <hi>Hereſie.</hi> And <hi>Spondanus</hi> inſinuates that <hi>Fulbertus</hi> in his Epiſtles to <hi>Leuthericus</hi> repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended him for diſſenting from the Catholicks in this point. But upon peruſing thoſe Epiſtles, as they are ſet out by <hi>Carolus de Villiers</hi> in the <hi>Bibliotheca Patrum,</hi> I find no ſuch thing. Some hard words in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:97031:24"/>
paſt upon the ſcore of Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Diſcipline;</hi> but as to this matter I can ſee nothing.</p>
            <p>Nor can I conceive how it ſhould be ſo; not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Fulbertus</hi> was <hi>Berengarius</hi> his Inſtructor, but becauſe his Writings ſhew him to have been of an Opinion quite <hi>different</hi> from, nay <hi>contrary</hi> to that of <hi>Paſchaſius;</hi> though indeed the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> would fain pull him on their ſide, becauſe he was of ſuch Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Eminence in his time, ſo greatly admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that ſome Dreaming Monks devis'd this plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Romance of him (which ſome Learned Writers too, have been willing to report) that <hi>when he was Sick, the Virgin</hi> Mary <hi>was ſeen to come and Suckle him with Milk out of her own Breaſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let us be ſerious. This <hi>Fulbertus</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>Chartres,</hi> in the Province of <hi>Leuthericus, Anno</hi> 1007. And the firſt thing to our purpoſe, which I find in his Epiſtle to <hi>Adeodatus</hi> is very remarkable. For ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving mentioned Three Things neceſſary to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, whereof this is the <hi>Third,</hi> viz. <hi>what the two Sacraments of life, that is of the Lords Body and Blood, do conſiſt of;</hi> preſently he ſaith, that <hi>many looking on this and other things too Carnally, while they gazed on a Carnal Senſe,</hi> (or, meaning) <hi>more than on the ſecret Myſteries of Faith, they tumbled down the precipice of a pernicious Errour.</hi> And is not this directly againſt the Carnal opinion of <hi>Paſchaſius,</hi> as well as againſt thoſe who lookt upon theſe Myſteries as <hi>Empty</hi> things? And after he ſaith, <hi>becauſe</hi> Chriſt <hi>was to take away into Heaven that Body which he offer'd up for us, that we might not want the help of his Body ſo taken away, he left us this Pledge of his Body and Blood; not the Symbol of an empty Myſtery, but that which a ſecret Vertue inviſibly works in under the viſible Form of a
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:97031:24"/>
Creature, the Holy Ghoſt joyning the True Body of Chriſt to it.</hi> You ſee <hi>Fulbertus</hi> runs clearly upon that <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical</hi> 
               <note place="margin">'Compaginante Spiritu Sancto Corpus Chriſti verum.</note> 
               <hi>Union</hi> I ſpake of before, which ſuppoſes the Subſtance and Nature both of Bread and Body to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main ſtill in themſelves <hi>diſtinct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In his Epiſtle <hi>ad Finardum</hi> he plainly diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that Body which Chriſt took in the Virgin's Womb, from that which is in the Sacrament: And at the End of his Sermons, he tells us, that <hi>ſome Eat to Life, and others to Deſtruction; but that the Thing repreſented by the Sacrament is to every Man for Life only, ſo that he who Eateh to his Condemnation, Eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not the Fleſh of Christ, nor Drinks his Blood al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he Eats and Drinks that which is the Sacrament of ſo great a thing.</hi> All which, how can it poſſibly conſiſt with the fulſome Doctrine of a Corporal pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, which ſuppoſes that very Fleſh and Blood which Chriſt took of the Virgin to be truly, Real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Subſtantially and materially in the Sacrament?</p>
            <p>This laſt paſſage in <hi>Fulbertus</hi> is probably thought to have been that, which did ſtick ſo deeply in the mind of his Scholar, <hi>Berengarius:</hi> Whoſe famous caſe I am at length come to, and ſhall ſearch into it impartially, though it be no ſmall unhappineſs that we muſt have recourſe to the Writings of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Adverſaries; there being little extant which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he wrote for himſelf, or his Friends for him, though it was a caſe wherein we may be ſure many Pens were at work: And ſo we are expreſly told by <hi>Sigebort,</hi> who lived near the time of this Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, that <hi>many diſputed much both in their Diſcourſes and Writings ſome</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Contra eum</hi> (Berengarium) <hi>&amp; pro eo multum à multis, &amp; Verbis &amp; Scriptis, diſputatum eſt.</hi> Sigeb. Chron. <hi>ad an.</hi> 1051.</note> 
               <hi>againſt</hi> Berengarius, <hi>and ſome for him:</hi> And the Truth of this will appear in the Sequel.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:97031:25"/>
Though ſome Romaniſts have endeavoured to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the Memory of <hi>Berengarius</hi> with a heavy weight of ill Characters (as 'tis uſual with them in all ſuch caſes) yet ſeveral of that ſide have ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly acknowledg'd, that he was a moſt Eminent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in his time, not only for his great Charity, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility and Auſterities of Life, but alſo for his great Parts and Learning. And the thing is evident, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from his Dignity in the Church; for he was Archdeacon of <hi>Angers</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> intruſted with the Office of Inſtructing the Clergy, and of training them up in the Studies of Divinity: And partly from thoſe great ſtirs which hapned in ſo many parts of Chriſtendom upon his Quarrel. Not that I can imagine ſuch hot contentions ſhould ariſe in <hi>France, England,</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> (as 'tis plain there were) purely upon the perſonal account of <hi>Berengarius:</hi> For it is impoſſible to conceive how one ſingle Frenchman, though of the greateſt Note could en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage ſuch diſtant Numbers in a common Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie by any New Doctrines of his own. No, their general Concurrence with him is a plain ſign, that they had a deeply radicated Love for the Ancient Truth, however it was Depreſt by the then prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Patrons of the <hi>Paſchaſian</hi> phancy; that they were well prepared for a publick Declaration of the Truth; and that they waited only for a fair Opportunity of declaring it, and for ſome ſuch Leading Man as <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rengarius</hi> was to appear in the Head of them. So you know it was at the time of the Reformationl peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple had had ſuch <hi>bitter</hi> Experience of the <hi>Spirit of Popery,</hi> that't was every where <hi>Hated,</hi> and the World was well diſpoſed for the entertainment of Chriſt's Religion; ſo that when <hi>Luther</hi> cryed out againſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:97031:25"/>
and Prieſt-craft, the cry went preſently round, not ſo much for <hi>Luthers</hi> ſake, as for the reſpect men had for <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>honeſty,</hi> and out of their dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of a <hi>Lucrative</hi> contrivance which ſome Popes and their fellow work men had formed to oppreſs the world. Thus a great part of Chriſtendom ſeems to have been diſpos'd in <hi>Berengarius</hi> his days, if that had been <hi>God's</hi> time for a general Reformation: But the Sins of the World were to be puniſh'd, and God in his Wiſdom choſe rather to bring good out of evil after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, than to <hi>prevent</hi> the evil at that time.</p>
            <p>As to <hi>Berengarius</hi> his Principles, I muſt intreat you to obſerve, that his <hi>Firſt</hi> opinion ſeems to have been, that the Bread and Wine are <hi>barely Figures and Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows,</hi> without the inviſible thing, if we may believe thoſe that wrote againſt him, <hi>Lancfranck, Adelman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Durandus</hi> of <hi>Liege,</hi> and eſpecially <hi>Guitmund.</hi> But ſearching more narrowly into this point, and finding how obnoxious he was to his adverſaries, who could not but object againſt him the ſenſe of the whole Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, his Opinion afterwards roſe <hi>higher,</hi> as to this, and his <hi>ſettled</hi> Judgement was, <hi>That the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lancfranck <hi>de Euchar. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cram.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sacrifice of the Church conſiſteth of two things, the viſible Sacrament, and the Thing of the Sacrament, that is, the ſpiritual Body of Chriſt,</hi> as the Ancients themſelves ſpake. And to this exactly agrees what <hi>Guitmund</hi> fairly ſaid of the <hi>Berengarians,</hi> that <hi>they were divided in their poſitive Opinions; ſome of them believing that there is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Berengariani multum in hoe differunt, quod alii nihil omnino de Corpore &amp; Sanguine Domini Sacramentis iſtis in eſſe, ſed tantummodo umbras hoec &amp; figur as eſſe dicant. Alii verò dicunt ibi Corpus &amp; Sanguinem Domini revera; ſed latenter continueri, &amp; ut ſumi poſſint quodammodo (ut ita dixerim) impanari. Et hanc ipſius <hi>Berengarii</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiliorem eſſe Sententiam aiunt, <hi>Guitmund,</hi> de Veritate Euchar. <hi>lib. 1.</hi> non procul ab initio.</note> 
               <hi>nothing at all of the Lords Body and Bloud in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, but that the Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bols are ſhadows and figures only; whereas others of them
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:97031:26"/>
confeſt the Lords Body and Blood to be there truly, but ſecretly, and as it were joyned with the Bread and Wine, that they may be received; which they ſay</hi> (ſaith <hi>Guitmund) is the more ſubtile Opinion of</hi> Berengarius <hi>himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that the main of the Controverſie, wherein <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rengarius</hi> and his Party where concern'd, lay in theſe two Negative Points, which are now the great Points in Controverſie between <hi>us,</hi> and the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> 1. They utterly oppoſed the <hi>Paſchaſian</hi> Error of a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Preſence. 2. They abſolutely denied any Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial change of the Nature and Subſtance of the Bread and Wine: For now the Evil began to ſwel to a very high degree: Tho I do <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſti enim licet inter ſe diverſi ſint, contra nos tamen unam habent penè ſententiam, &amp; argumentis nituntur eiſdem. Utriſque enim nibil de pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne &amp; vino mutari eſſentialiter aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt.</hi> Id.</note> not yet find the <hi>word</hi> uſed, yet the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> of Tranſubſtantiation began now in this Age, in the 11. Century to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced, as an <hi>Additional</hi> Doctrine which ſome endeavoured to obtrude upon the World, becauſe they found it impoſſible for them to maintain their new <hi>Paſchaſian</hi> conceit of a corporal Preſence, without maintaining luſtily this <hi>Newer</hi> fancy of a <hi>ſubſtantial change</hi> of the Sacramental Elements.</p>
            <p>But the extream Novelty of this Opinion will eaſily appear from theſe following Conſiderations. 1. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De ſacr. Euch.</hi> lib. 1. cap. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> tho he ſeldome yields any thing that is againſt him, and when he doth 'tis with a ſparing hand and againſt His own Will; yet he confeſſeth that <hi>Berengarius was not reputed the firſt Inventer of his Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,</hi> as he is pleaſed to call it. <hi>Durandus</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Liege,</hi> who wrote againſt <hi>Berengari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Qualiter</hi> Bruno Andegaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis <hi>Epiſcopus, item</hi> Berengarius Turonenſis, <hi>antiquas hoereſes modernis temporibus introducen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> &amp;c. Durand. <hi>Ep ad</hi> Henr. 1.</note> and was his Contemporary, reckons it among thoſe <hi>old</hi> Hereſies, which he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed <hi>Bruno</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Angers,</hi> and <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rengarius</hi> for reviving at that time. You
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:97031:26"/>
muſt make the man allowance for the word, <hi>Heriſie:</hi> It was a ſcolding expreſſion which ſome uſed in thoſe days for want of ſtrong Arguments: But if you ſtrip the Malice and Virulency off, the naked and true mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, that <hi>Berengarius</hi> held an <hi>Ancient opinion,</hi> and you may eaſily ſee it by comparing his <hi>laſt</hi> judgement with the Faith of the Ancients. 2. Tho' ſome pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Doctors of the Roman Church ſtrove at that time to Eſtabliſh the Doctrine of the <hi>Corporal</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and to Introduce the other, of a Subſtantial Change of the Holy Symbols in the Euchariſt, yet theſe Inovations were ſo far from being generally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, that the Writers of thoſe times, nay on that very ſide, ſufficently ſhew us, how diſtracted the world was about thoſe points, and what vaſt numbers in ſeveral parts of Chriſtendome ſided with <hi>Berengarius. Durandus</hi> in his fierce Sanguinary Letter to <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt of <hi>France,</hi> call'd the <hi>Berengarian</hi> Faith, <hi>the foul reproach of his whole moſt Noble Kingdom.</hi> And <note place="margin">Totius nobiliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſime regni veſtri (heu nimis tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe) opprobium.</note> hearing that the <hi>Berengarians</hi> defired to be heard in a publick Council, and that King <hi>Henry</hi> had ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon'd a Council in order to it, he diſſwaded him from that courſe, becauſe (as he told the King) <hi>He and others were very much afraid, leaſt the</hi> Berengari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and <hi>ſhould come off, and ſo the laſt State of things would be worſe than the firſt;</hi> therefore he beſought the King to puniſh them <hi>unheard.</hi> After <hi>this</hi> Man, <hi>Guit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund</hi> tells us, that not the <hi>Berengarians</hi> only, but ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>others,</hi> though Enemies to the <hi>Berengarians,</hi> were very much <hi>divided</hi> in their ſenſe about the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament; <hi>ſome believing the Bread and Wine to be changed in part only; others imagining, that though there ſhould be an entire change, yet where there are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Receivers, the Sacrament Returns into Bread
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:97031:27"/>
and Wine again,</hi> Some years after <hi>Algerus,</hi> ſpeaks of <note place="margin">Alger. Prolog. <hi>in Librum de Sacrament.</hi>
               </note> no leſs than ſix different opinions about the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, beſides that <hi>New</hi> Opinion which now begun to ſpread. <hi>Some held no other change to be in the Symbols, than is in the Water at Baptiſm. Others held ſuch an Union between Chriſt and the Symbols, as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween his Divinity and his Fleſh. Others held a change of them to be into the Fleſh and Blood not of Chriſt, but of ſome Son of Man who is acceptable unto God. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers believed that no change could be made by a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Prieſt. Others again, that though there were a change, yet it doth not continue, but that there is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn into Bread and Wine; And others again, that the Sacrament is Digeſted, and doth Corrupt after eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> All theſe hot Diſputes, which naturally ſprang out of the Bowels of a groſs opinion, ſo full of ſenſible difficulties, did plainly ſhew it to be a quite different thing from the Faith of the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Church, when there were none of theſe quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rols becauſe the prolyſick Doctrine which Naturally brought them into the World was not then in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: for had it been ſo, thoſe many difficulties it neceſſarily yields, muſt have brought forth abundance of Diſputes; eſpecially in times when Men had a greater <hi>Liberty</hi> of diſputing, than in <hi>Berengarius</hi> his Days, when the Pope and his party had uſurped and did not ſtick to exerciſe a Tyrannical power over Princes themſelves.</p>
            <p>But of all theſe diſagreeing parties, they that ſtuck to <hi>Berengarius</hi> was the moſt formidable Body to the innovating Faction. <hi>Sigebert</hi> ſhews that <hi>all</hi> France <hi>abounded with them. William</hi> of <hi>Malmesbury,</hi> though a hater of <hi>Berengarius</hi> his memory, tells us the <hi>ſame</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Malmesbur. <hi>ad an.</hi> 1087.</note> thing; ſo doth <hi>Matthew Paris;</hi> and <hi>Matthew</hi> of <hi>Weſt-miniſter</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:97031:27"/>
faith, that Berengarius <hi>had almoſt corrupted</hi> (as his Language is) <hi>all the French, Italian, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh.</hi> And indeed the vaſt endeavours the Popes u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſuppreſs the Ancient Faith, not in thoſe Countries only, but in <hi>Germany</hi> too, plainly ſhews that their Innovations did not gain ground without meeting with ſtrong oppoſition, how lightly ſoever <hi>Lanfranck</hi> and <hi>Guitmund</hi> ſpeak of this matter, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby to diſgrace <hi>Berengarius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. Nay, It is very obſervable, as a further plain ſign of the Novelty of Tranſubſtantiation, that the very Men who were the <hi>Patrons</hi> of it found ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perplexities in bringing it to its form, that they could not agree among themſelves, but ſpake incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtently, ſo that it coſt them much time to mould the abſurdity into the ſhape, wherein it appears now: And this I ſhall ſhew you as briefly as the Matter will give me leave, according to the Series of <hi>time:</hi> The beſt Key to open the whole thing, and the only way of doing right to <hi>Berengarius</hi> his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory and Cauſe.</p>
            <p>It being found by his Letters to <hi>Lanfranck</hi> then Abbot of <hi>Caen</hi> in <hi>Normandy,</hi> that he was againſt the Opinion of <hi>Paſchaſius,</hi> it was thought he held the Sacred Symbols to be nothing but <hi>empty</hi> Types and ſhadows; which, as I ſaid, <hi>perhaps</hi> might have been his <hi>firſt</hi> Opinion. Hereupon, to make him an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to all of that perſwaſion. Several Synods were called one after another, at <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Verceil Anno</hi> 1050. under <hi>Leo</hi> the <hi>9th</hi> beſides ſeveral other Aſſemblies which <hi>Mabillon</hi> mentions; in ſome of <note place="margin">Mabillon <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. vet.</hi> Tom. 2. p. 477. &amp;c.</note> which Synods <hi>Berengarius</hi> was condemned, though <hi>abſent.</hi> Now to give you my free thoughts, and to be juſt to all parties, very probable it is, that they
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:97031:28"/>
condemned him thus only upon his <hi>Firſt ſuppoſed</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, and therein indeed they ſeem to have been <hi>unanimous.</hi> My Reaſons are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For in the Synod at <hi>Tours</hi> under Pope <hi>Victor</hi> II. <hi>Anno</hi> 1056. where and when <hi>Berengarius</hi> appeared in perſon, he own'd his Correct Opinion, which in common conſtruction amounts to no more but a <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Citat. ab Uſſer deſucc. &amp; ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu,</hi> cap. 7. p. 201.</note> Confeſſion of the <hi>Real Spiritual preſence,</hi> that the Bread and Wine do become <hi>not umbratically, but tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Fleſh and Blood of Chriſt.</hi> This doth not fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour either Tranſubſtantiation, or a Corporal Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and yet this gave ſatisfaction, ſo that he was <hi>not only diſmiſt, but kindly received into the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Guitmund. <hi>de Sacram.</hi> lib. 3.</note> 
               <hi>of the Roman Church,</hi> ſaith <hi>Guitmund.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Mabillon</hi> tells us of another ſhort Confeſſion which he ſaw in a Manuſcript, and which is ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <note place="margin">Mabillon <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect.</hi> Tom. 2. p. 487.</note> to have been voluntarily drawn up by <hi>Berengari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> and preſented to <hi>Gregory</hi> the <hi>7th. Anno</hi> 1078. <hi>that the Bread is the true Body of Chriſt, and the Wine his true Blood</hi> Nor doth this Confeſſion reach to the buſineſs of Tranſubſtantiation, without ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it after a moſt violent manner, but only aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts the Truth of Chriſt's preſence in the Sacrament in oppoſition to a bare Type or ſhadow; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Mabillon</hi> himſelf doth acknowledg, that this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion was <hi>Artificially and cunningly worded:</hi> And though all this fell ſhort of the <hi>New</hi> Opinion then, ſo that it ſatisfied not the <hi>bigotted</hi> Men at <hi>Rome,</hi> yet it gave ſatisfaction to <hi>others,</hi> nay to the Pope himſelf, ſo that the Caſe of <hi>Berengarius</hi> was put off to further conſideration another year.</p>
            <p>Now if the matter was thus (as in all probability it was) I cannot ſee what hurt this doth <hi>Berengarius</hi>'s Reputation, or why thy Romaniſts ſhould take occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:97031:28"/>
hence to roar againſt him ſo for a perfidious and perjur'd perſon, when in theſe inſtances he declared his <hi>ripened and deliberate</hi> judgment, as far as the belief of a <hi>Real preſence</hi> went, to which, as far as I can find, he was conſtant all his Life time. Nor do I ſee what advantage thoſe Condemnations of him in his abſence can bring to the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thoſe Synods ſeem to have been ſo zealouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd only for the Catholick Doctrine of the <hi>real pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,</hi> and to have been unanimous as to that <hi>ſole</hi> point not underſtanding rightly the ſenſe either of <hi>Scotus</hi> or <hi>Berengarius.</hi> For when the buſineſs was carried <hi>further</hi> from a <hi>real</hi> to a <hi>Corporal</hi> preſence, and from the belief of the main <hi>Thing</hi> to a belief of the <hi>Modus;</hi> I mean, when once it came to be urged that Chriſt's Body is <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantially</hi> and <hi>Materially</hi> in the Sacrament, and that by a <hi>Subſtantial Converſion</hi> of the very <hi>Nature</hi> of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments into it; when the matter was brought to this height <hi>Berengarius</hi>'s very <hi>Judges</hi> blunder'd miſerably, and were much <hi>divided</hi> about it, and inconſiſtent with themſelves. Thus we are expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly told by <hi>Zacharias Chryſopolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Sunt nonnulli, imd forſan multi, ſed vix no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tari poſſunt, qui cum damnato <hi>Berengario</hi> i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ſentiant, &amp; tamen eundem cum Eccleſia damnant. In hoc videlicet damnant eum, quia formam verborum Eccleſioe abjiciens, nuditate ſermonis ſeandalum movebat. Non ſequebatur, ut dicunt, uſum ſcripturarum, quoe paſſim res ſignificantes tanquam ſignificatas appellant, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertim in Sacramentis Zachar. <hi>Chryſopol.</hi> in concord. Evangel. <hi>lib. 4. cap. 156. BB. PP.</hi> Soec. 12.</note> in the next Age, <hi>That there were ſome, yea perhaps many, who held the ſame Opinion with</hi> Beren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garius <hi>although they condemned him. In this thing they condemned him, that laying aſide the Churches way of ſpeaking he gave offence by his open manner of expreſſing himſelf. He did not obſerve the Language of Scripture, which frequently gives the Name of the thing ſignified to that which ſignifies it, eſpecially in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments.</hi> This was the only quarrel which many had againſt him, who as to his Doctrine perfectly concurr'd and agreed with him. The truth is, <hi>Berengarius</hi> his
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:97031:29"/>
Judges were much to ſeek, what to ſay to him, or how to deal with him, when he appeared <hi>perſonally</hi> before them. Of which we have two plain inſtances in Two Synods at <hi>Rome,</hi> the one under <hi>Nicolas</hi> the Second <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1059. the other under <hi>Gregory</hi> the <hi>7th</hi> in <hi>February</hi> 1079.</p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe two Synods was called chiefly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Election of Popes, and againſt Simony, which was then a great <hi>Trade</hi> at <hi>Rome.</hi> Thither <hi>Berengarius</hi> was ſummon'd; and there he defended himſelf with ſuch irroſiſtible Evidence of truth againſt a material change in the <note place="margin">Nicolaus <hi>Papa comperiens te docere panem vinumque altaris poſt Conſecrationem ſine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriali mutatione in priſtinis eſſentiis rema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere, conceſſâ tibi reſpondendi licentid,</hi> &amp;c. Lankfranc. <hi>de Euchar. adv.</hi> Berengarium, <hi>Eique</hi> (Berengario) <hi>cum nullus valeret obſiſtere,</hi> Albericus <hi>evocatur ad Synodum,</hi> &amp;c. Leo <hi>Oſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſis in Chronic.</hi> Caſſinenſ. lib. 3. c. 33.</note> Sacrament, that he quite confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the whole Synod though it conſiſted of no leſs than 113 Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops. Not a man of them had a word to ſay againſt his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; ſo that they were forced to ſend for <hi>Albericus,</hi> a Cardinal Deacon, and a man of great reputation for his Learning: But he was ſo confounded too, that he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a Weeks time to write againſt <hi>Berengarius. Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>franck</hi> (who relates things partially, as the modern Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts have done after him) not only omits the main of this ſtory, but falſifies one part of it, as if <hi>Berenga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> had not anſwer'd for himſelf, though the Pope had given him leave: Whereas <hi>Leo Oſtienſis,</hi> who lived a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout that time relates the particulars of the ſtory; and <hi>Sigonius</hi> confirms it; nay <hi>Guitmund</hi> himſelf, though a bitter Adverſary to <hi>Berengarius,</hi> owns there was a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict in that Synod: All which the Learned Biſhop <hi>Uſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> 
               <note place="margin">De <hi>ſucceſ. &amp; ſtatu cap.</hi> 7.</note> has noted to my hands.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, after all this <hi>Berenga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Elegiſti-palam atque in audientia Sancti Concilii orthodoxam fidem non amore veritatis, ſed timore mortis confiteri. <hi>Lanfrane.</hi> de Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char. in initio.</note> recanted in that Synod meerly for fear of Death: An Argument that even great Men are ſubject
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:97031:29"/>
to humane ſrailty, eſpecially in extremity of danger, tho' the <hi>ſcandal</hi> of his complyance falls upon that cauſe; which needed Fire and Faggot for its laſt Argument, and an Executioner inſtead of a Diſputant to bring it to a Concluſion. But obſerve, what a <hi>Blunder</hi> theſe Men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in this their Sanguinary attempt on behalf of the New Opinion. <hi>Humbertus</hi> was order'd by the Pope to draw up the Form of a Confeſſion; the Synod ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved it; and poor <hi>Berengarius</hi> to ſave his Life was forced to ſubſcribe it: Now the Confeſſion was this in ſhort, <hi>That the Bread and Wine which are ſet upon the Altar, after</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Conſentio autem ſanctoe Romanoe Eccleſioe—ſcilicet Panem &amp; Vinum quoe in altari ponun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, poſt Conſecrationem non ſolum Sacramentum, ſed etiam verum Corpus &amp; Sanguinem Domini nostri Jeſu Chriſti eſſe, &amp; ſenſualiter non ſolum Sacramento ſed in veritate manibus Sacerdotum tractari, frangi, &amp; fidelium dentibus atteri. <hi>Lanſranc. Alger. &amp;</hi> alii multi.</note> 
               <hi>Conſecration are not only the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but alſo the true Body and Blood of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; that</hi> (this true Body) <hi>is ſenſually not only in the Sacrament, but in Truth handled and broken by the hands of the Prieſts, and ground or torn, by the Teeth of the Faithful.</hi> This was very harſh; for it renders Chriſt liable to New Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings every day, it is inconſiſtent with the <hi>finer</hi> Notion of the preſence of Chriſt's Body after the manner of a <hi>Spirit,</hi> it introduces ſuch a <hi>craſs</hi> ſort of Eating as our Saviour rebuked the <hi>Capernaites</hi> for thinking of; it makes us to be not only Eaters of a <hi>Sacrament,</hi> but in very Truth Eaters of <hi>Mans Fleſh.</hi> Therefore the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Church of <hi>Rome</hi> will not ſtand to theſe Expreſſions; divers of her Doctors formerly have renounced this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition as <hi>erronous and abſurd,</hi> though it was made by the Pope <hi>in Cathedra</hi> and in a publick Synod, the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Writers have been lamentably put to it how to give it a Tolerable conſtruction: The <hi>Gloſſator</hi> upon the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees confeſſeth, that if it be not <hi>underſtood in a ſound ſenſe, it leads into a greater Hereſie, than what Berenga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius himſelf was charged with.</hi> But the Doctrine being a
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:97031:30"/>
Novelty, they knew not as yet how to expreſs it wari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enough. Caution comes by <hi>experience,</hi> and 'tis the meeting with objections that puts men upon a neceſſity of digeſting their Notions better; therefore it is no wonder that the conceits of theſe Men were crude, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were not yet throughly conſider'd and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted. <hi>As time</hi> and <hi>debates</hi> ſhew'd them their Errour, ſo they became ſenſible and aſham'd of it. For tho' <hi>Guitmund</hi> endeavour'd to deſend thoſe raw Expreſſions, and with the courſeſt and boldeſt Explications that I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver read, yet all he could do, could not make the thing palateable; the very men of thoſe times that were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd for the New Opinion took diſtaſte at the <hi>defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> as appears by this. For at the next Synod at <hi>Rome</hi> under <hi>Gregory</hi> the Seventh, twenty years after when <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rengarius</hi> was ſummon'd <hi>again,</hi> and another Confeſſion was prepared for him to ſubſcribe, this foul Notion of <hi>ſenſually handling, breaking, and grinding the true body of Chriſt</hi> was quite dropt; nor was a word of it mention'd; but the Doctrine they compell'd him to ſign by fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the poor Old Man with Death, was this, <hi>That the Bread and Wine which are ſet upon the Altar are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantially converted into the true and proper and quickning Fleſh and Blood of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; and after Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration are the true Body of Chriſt, which was born of the Virgin, and which was offer'd up upon the Croſs for the Salvation of the World, and which ſits at the right hand of the Father,</hi> &amp;c. Here was the Paſchaſian Opinion <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved</hi> now at length into <hi>Tranſubſtantiation;</hi> and this they thought was a <hi>Correct</hi> Confeſſion, not liable to ſo many Objections as they found that was which had been contrived by Pope <hi>Nicolas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet it is obſervable, that <hi>before</hi> this <hi>New</hi> Cunfeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was drawn up, it is acknowledged by the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> themſelves that there were very warm <hi>diſputes</hi> in
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:97031:30"/>
this Synod, and that not ſo much about the <hi>wording</hi> of the Confeſſion, as about the <hi>Opinion</hi> it ſelf; many of them believing one thing and ſome another. <hi>The greateſt part of them affirmed the Bread and Wine after</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Concil.</hi> Rom. <hi>ſub</hi> Greg. 7.</note> 
               <hi>conſecration to be Subſtantially changed into that Body of our Lord which was born of the Virgin: but ſome endeav. oured to maintain that it is a Figure only,</hi> &amp;c. Indeed this party was over power'd by the other; neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it plainly appears, that neither the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, nor that of the Corporal preſence prevailed ſo yet, but that there were <hi>ſeveral</hi> in this <hi>Synod</hi> who believed <hi>neither.</hi> Nay, tho ſome late Romaniſts have had the confidence to deny it, I ſee no reaſon we have to diſcredit thoſe who have poſitively affirmed, that Pope <hi>Gregory himſelf</hi> doubted much in this point. <hi>Engelbert</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Treves</hi> (as Sever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of our Authors have obſerved) conſeſſeth, <hi>that this</hi> Gregory <hi>queſtioned whether that which is received at the Lords Table be the True body and bloud of Chriſt.</hi> Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Benno</hi> who wrote the life of this <hi>Gregory</hi> tells us (and the Romaniſts themſelves own the Book to be genuine) <hi>that he commanded all the Cardinals to keep a ſtrict Faſt, to beg of God that he would ſhew by ſome Signe, whether the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>or</hi> Berengarius <hi>were in the right opinion touching the body of our Lord in the Sacrament.</hi> Nay <hi>Conradus</hi> the Abbot of <hi>Urſperg</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, how that Synod which began at <hi>Mentz</hi> and was <note place="margin">Vide Concil. <hi>Brixien.</hi> Anno 1080. apud <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium.</hi>
               </note> removed to <hi>Breſcia Anno</hi> 1080 depoſed this <hi>Gregory,</hi> as for many other things, ſo for this in particular, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>he called in queſtion the Catholick and Apoſtolick faith concerning the body of our Lord, and was an old diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of the Heretick</hi> Berengarius (as they were pleas'd to ſpeak.) To all which the ſticklers for Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation have nothing to ſay, but this, that theſe are lies and calumnies invented by <hi>Benno</hi> and <hi>Conradus;</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:97031:31"/>
which is a <hi>ſenſleſs</hi> ſhift, and the ſame thing in effect as if they told us, they are reſolved to contradict mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of fact though it be related by their own party, and diſown every thing that hurts their cauſe, or but touches the credit of any one of their Popes, though he were a very wicked wretch, as every one knows this Pope <hi>Gregory,</hi> or <hi>Hildebrand</hi> was.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Allix</hi> hath lately given us a paſſage out of a Manuſcript piece of this <hi>Hildebrands</hi> now in the Libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> which is enough to put the matter out of controverſie, and to juſtifie theſe allegations: his <note place="margin">Proefat. ad de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminat. <hi>Joan. Pariſ. pag. 7.</hi> Cum autem Panis &amp; Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num dicantur a cunctis Sanctis, &amp; a fidelibus creditur tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in Subſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Corporis &amp; Sanguinis Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sti, quâ fit illa converſio, an for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malis an Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantialis quere ſolet? Quod au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem formalis non fit, manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum eſt, quod forma Panis &amp; Vini remanet. Utrum vero ſit Subſtantialis; perſpicuum non eſt.</note> words are theſe, <hi>That whereas</hi> (ſays he) <hi>the Bread and Wine are ſaid to paſs into the ſubſtance of Chriſts Body and Blood, a queſtion is wont to ariſe, how this converſion is made, whether it be a Formal or a Subſtantial change? That it is not a formal one is manifeſt, becauſe the form of Bread and Wine remains: But whether it be a Subſtantial one, is not manifeſt.</hi> I know ſome ſubtle notions and ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inconſiſtences do follow there, which may puzzle a Reader how to underſtand them: But what can any man gather from theſe words <hi>(whether it be a Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial change, is not manifeſt)</hi> but this, that there were in this Pope <hi>Gregory</hi>'s time ſeveral <hi>queſtions</hi> about the change in the Sacrament, and that he <hi>himſelf</hi> was not able to reſolve them, but was inclined to believe, that the change is <hi>not</hi> Subſtantial.</p>
            <p>That I cannot give you a more perfect and exact account of all the particulars relating to this Synod and this Pope, is, becauſe ſome have been very careful to ſuppreſs them, and have given us no other account of them than what they pleas'd themſelves. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the <hi>Age</hi> wherein theſe things were tranſacted was ſo barbarous, and the <hi>Books</hi> I have ſearched are of that ſort, that no man would willingly moyl in ſuch a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren ſtudy, but out of an earneſt deſire to pick out what
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:97031:31"/>
matter of <hi>Fast</hi> he could, and to digeſt it right: which is the only buſineſs before me now in tracing the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Tranſubſtantion. And upon the whole you cannot but eaſily diſern, what <hi>ſhifts</hi> the Patrons of it were put to, what <hi>Arts</hi> they were forced to uſe, what <hi>perplexities</hi> they found in their way, what <hi>Heats and diſtractions</hi> hapned among them, before they could make it be belived in the Roman Church her ſelf, tho' in times that were not only ſcandalous for Ignorance, and conſequently very Receptive of the groſſeſt Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours; but Infamous alſo for all thoſe many violences and oppreſſions, which commonly attend a blind Zeal. Many even of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> verily thought that then the Divel was let looſe, and that prediction fulfilled <hi>Apocal.</hi> 20. that <hi>after the expiation of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years Satan ſhould be looſed out of his Priſon, and ſhould go about to deceive the Nations which are in the four quarters of the Earth.</hi> Such commotions and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions then hapned in the world, eſpecially in the Papacy of this <hi>Gregory,</hi> as if the Prince were come a broad with ſtormes and tempſts to mingle Heaven and Earth together. This was the Pope of whom ſuch <hi>Horrid,</hi> yet <hi>true</hi> Characters were given by ſome of the very Romiſh Communion, that it would weary one to tranſcribe but the half part. The Pope who decreed, <hi>that the Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>alone is to be called Univerſal; that He alone can depoſe all Biſhops, that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vidr Registir.</hi> Gregor. 7. lib. 2.</note> 
               <hi>He only can uſe the Imperial Arms that all Princes are to kiſs his feet, that 'tis Lawful for him to depoſe Emperors, that an unlimited power of Ordination is in him, that no Synod may be called a general Council without his command, that no Chapter nor Book is to be acounted canonical with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Authority, that there is no appeal from his Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, that he can be judged by none, that the Roman Church never did, never can Err, that by his leave Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:97031:32"/>
may call their Princes to account, that be can abſolve Subjects from their Allegiance, and</hi> the like.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding all theſe terrible uſurpations many were Thunder-proof ſtill. One Synod at <hi>Worms con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd</hi> the Pope, another at <hi>Pavia excommunicated</hi> him; a third at <hi>Breſcia depoſed</hi> him. Setting aſide thoſe Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers at the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> who did not ſtick <hi>to</hi> proſtitute their Conſciences to their Intereſt and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition: men of all ranks, orders, and degrees made the world ring with their out-cries. Princes began now to reſiſt the Pope, being too late ſenſible, that what power their exceſſive zeal had given him, he armed himſelf with againſt his over kind Benefactors, ſo that there was no ſuch Enemy to Crowns, as the Tripple Diadem: the Biſhops finding themſelves robb'd of their juſt authority, by one Uſurper, oppoſed him to his Face. The whole conſiderate world Groan'd and Wept for the abominations in <hi>Babylon,</hi> complain'd of the Errours and Corruption which had crept into the Church, longed for a Redreſs of abuſes, and would fain have had a Reformation, but could not obtain it, being hindred by a potent Faction, who ſhould have Cured the Common Diſeaſe, but were themſelves the greateſt Plague.</p>
            <p>Among other Innovations, the New Doctrine of the Sacrament was ſtill oppoſed. For to go on: Tho' <hi>Berengarius</hi> died about nine years after the Synod at <hi>Rome,</hi> yet the Truth expired not with him. I confeſs in the Twelfth Century the <hi>word</hi> Tranſubſtantiation was uſed by <hi>Stephen</hi> who was Biſhop of <hi>Autun</hi> in <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy,</hi> about <hi>Anno</hi> 1120 and as far as I can yet find, the <hi>Firſt</hi> that uſed it. And it is no wonder if the Doctrine which went along with it found entertainment, when it was ſent abroad by thoſe, whoſe Favour ſome were willing to expect, and whoſe diſpleaſure all had Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:97031:32"/>
to be afraid of. Nevertheleſs it made not ſuch a progreſs, but that divers Men of Note had the Heart and Honeſty to oppoſe it ſtill; I mean in the Weſtern Churches; for to other Countries it was as yet perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a ſtranger, whatever ſome have vainly pretended to the contrary.</p>
            <p>Several of <hi>Our</hi> Writers have ſo critically obſerved the variety of Opinions about the Sacrament in this Age, that I cannot hope to diſcover any thing New to Men of ſuch ſort of Learning; nor indeed do they need it. For your ſake therefore who may not be ſo well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the ſtate of thoſe times, I ſhall content my ſelf in giving you a Conciſe account of it, as a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector for the moſt part, or rather as an <hi>Abbreviator</hi> of what has been already Noted by others, whoſe Books have not been yet anſwer'd, that I know of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heriger</hi> Abbot of <hi>Lobes</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> who dyed in the beginning of this Twelfth Century, <hi>gather'd together many things which had been written by Catholick Fathers</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Sigebert. <hi>de Script. Excleſ.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>of the body and blood of Chriſt againſt</hi> Paſchaſius Rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus. <hi>Thuanus</hi> in his Epiſtle Dedicatory to <hi>Hen.</hi> the Fourth tells him, that <hi>Bruno</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Treves</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled ſeveral <hi>Berengarians</hi> out of <hi>Liege, Antwerp</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places thereabouts; and that this was <hi>Anno</hi> 1106. (for ſo Biſhop <hi>Uſher</hi> and <hi>Abbertine</hi> ſay it ſhould be read, becauſe <hi>Bruno</hi> was not Archbiſhop there till after <note place="margin">Uſher <hi>de ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſ &amp; Stat. c.</hi> 7. Abbert. <hi>de Euchar.</hi> p. 959.</note> the year 1106) <hi>Rupertus</hi> Abbot of <hi>Deutſch</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> about <hi>Anno</hi> 1110 is acknowledg'd by ſeveral Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts themſelves to have been for the <hi>myſtical Union</hi> I ſpake of before, againſt Tranſubſtantiation and the Corporal Preſence; and the thing is clear out of divers places in his Writings. <hi>Honorius</hi> of <hi>Auguſtodunum</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Anno</hi> 1120 is charged by <hi>Thomas Waldenſis</hi> (under the Character of the Author <hi>de Officiis)</hi> for a Favourer of <hi>Berengarius</hi> his Doctrine, and one of <hi>Rabanus</hi> his <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sive gemma a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimoe ext. in</hi> BB. PP.</note>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:97031:33"/>
Bread Eaters. <hi>Algerus</hi> who Flouriſht <hi>Anno</hi> 1130 (a Man ſo cryed up by the Romaniſts, for Writing againſt <hi>Berengarius,</hi> and for Tranſubſtantiation) reckons up, as <note place="margin">Prolog. <hi>ad Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>br. de Sacram.</hi>
               </note> I Noted before, <hi>Six ſeveral Opinions about the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that were common in his time, beſides that which he held himſelf.</hi> And, as I obſerved too, <hi>Zacharias Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopolitanus,</hi> who was towards the year 1160. tells us, that <hi>there were ſome, perhaps many, who then held</hi> Beren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garius <hi>his Opinion, though they blamed him for his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncommon way of expreſſing himſelf.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Si autem quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritur, qualis ſit illa converſio: An formalis, an Subſtantialis, an alterius ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neris? Definire non ſufficio.</hi> P. Lombard. <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiar.</hi> lib 4. diſt. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Peter Lombard</hi> about the ſame time, having reckon'd up vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Doctrines about this matter, and among the reſt that againſt Tranſubſtantiation in particular, though he himſelf held the <hi>Corporal Preſence,</hi> yet as to the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on about the <hi>Change</hi> of the Symbols, he plainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, as <hi>Gregory</hi> the Seventh had done, <hi>that he could not tell whether it be Subſtantial, or a change of another Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that which convinceth me more, that the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers of the New Opinion were very numerous and formidable at this time is, becauſe the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> began preſently after this to uſe <hi>Terrible</hi> and <hi>Outragious</hi> Methods againſt them, and for many years together carried on theſe Methods with a very quick Hand: Which as it ſhews plainly that <hi>other</hi> Arguments <hi>failed</hi> them now, and that they had no ſecurity left them but downright <hi>Violence,</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſion;</hi> ſo it ſhews too what great <hi>Fears</hi> they were under, leaſt the Old Opinion ſhould prevail <hi>again,</hi> notwithſtanding all their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours hitherto. Witneſs their proceedings againſt the <hi>Albigenſes;</hi> of whom I may hereafter give you a ſaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Account; but at preſent it ſhall be ſufficient for me to tell you from ſome of the Romaniſts themſelves that they were ſuch a ſort of people as were afterwards upon the Reſormation called <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> All that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:97031:33"/>
the Corruptions, or diſſented from the Errours of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in thoſe days, were compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended <note place="margin">Petrus <hi>Ciſterci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſis Monachus, qui de</hi> Albigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibus <hi>viſa ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorataque in hiſtoriam retu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit,</hi> Innocentio <hi>tertio Pontifici dicatam, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticos Toloſates, atque aliarum <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbium &amp; oppidorum, eorumque protectores communi nomine</hi> Albigenſes <hi>vocari conſueviſſe ait ab uſu loquentium,</hi> Marian. <hi>Prefat. ad</hi> Lucan. Tudenſ.</note> under the Common Name of the <hi>Albigenſes.</hi> The Numbers of them were ſo vaſt, that <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ferè enim nulla eſt terra, in quâ haec ſecta non ſit.</hi> Reinet. <hi>cont.</hi> Wald. c. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Reinerus</hi> their Perſecutor ingenuouſly confeſt, there was hardly any Nation, wherein this <hi>Sect</hi> (as he call'd them) <hi>was not.</hi> Let us now take a ſhort view of the proceedings againſt them.</p>
            <p>In the time of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Third <hi>Anno</hi> 1163. a Synod met at <hi>Tours</hi> in <hi>France</hi> chiefly againſt the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror <hi>Frederick</hi> and Victor the Anti-Pope; in which Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod a Canon was made againſt the <hi>Albigenſes, that no Man ſhould dare under the dreadful pain of an Anathema</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>to allow them Houſe or Harbour, or have any Commerce with them, or ſhew them any kind of Humanity.</hi> The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this ſeverity was grounded on ſtrong jealouſies they had of the dangers that might come from the great growth of theſe <hi>Albigenſis; whoſe Hereſie</hi> (as they ſaid in the beginning of that Canon) <hi>had ſpread like a gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grene from</hi> Tolouſe <hi>and the parts about it, through</hi> Gaſ <hi>coygny and ſeveral other Provinces. Anno</hi> 1170. a certain <note place="margin">Uſſer <hi>de ſucceſ. &amp; ſtat. p.</hi> 240.</note> Cardinal was ſent into the Province of <hi>Tolouſe</hi> to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs them by force of Arms. This courſe failing ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Synod in <hi>France</hi> was held againſt them. <hi>Anno</hi> 1176. which <hi>Binius</hi> calls a <hi>Gallican</hi> Council <hi>indefinitely;</hi> but <hi>Labbey</hi> ſpecifies the place, calling it <hi>Concilium Lumbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſe,</hi> or a Synod at <hi>Lombers,</hi> in the Archbiſhoprick of <hi>Tolouſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this Age infinite Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quippe in latiſſimis</hi> Galliae, Hiſpaniae, Italiae, Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> 
                  <hi>Provinciis tam multi hâc peste (Publicano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum) infecti eſſe dicuntur, ut ſecundum Prophetam, multiplicate eſſe ſuper numerum arenae videbantur.</hi> Guil. Novoburg. <hi>a clar.</hi> Uſſerio <hi>citat. de ſucceſſ.</hi> cap. 8. p. 238.</note> of Chriſtians, in <hi>France, Spain, Italy, Germany,</hi> and <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> made Publick profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:97031:34"/>
of the Old Faith againſt Tranſubſtantiation; tho they were called by ſeveral Names, for ſeveral Reaſons; as the <hi>Albigenſes, Cathariſts, Leoniſts, Publicans, Pata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens,</hi> and divers Names more, which their Enemies fixt upon them. But chiefly they abounded in the Southern Parts of <hi>France:</hi> And ſeeing Force and open Violence had hitherto had very little Succeſs againſt them, at laſt they were <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quia in</hi> Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conia, Albige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio <hi>&amp; partibus</hi> Toloſanis <hi>&amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liis lecis, ita Hereticorum, quos alii</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharos, <hi>alii</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinos, <hi>alii</hi> Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licanos, <hi>alii a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liis Nominibus vocant invaluit damnata per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitas, ut jam non in occulto, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut alibi ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitiam ſuam exerceant, ſed errores ſuos pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licam manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent, &amp; ad conſenſum ſuum ſimplices, attrahant &amp; infirmos; eas &amp; defenſores corum &amp; receptares Anathema decernimus ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacere. Concil.</hi> Lateran. <hi>Can</hi> 27.</note> Anathematiz'd by Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the Third and his party <hi>Anno</hi> 1179. in the <hi>Lateran</hi> Council at <hi>Rome.</hi> But being neither daunted nor frightned at this Thunderbolt, one <note n="‖" place="margin">Henricus <hi>a Papa</hi> Alexandro <hi>miſſus fuit in</hi> Gaſconiam, <hi>ad delendam hereticorum perfidiam altaris Sacramentum non credentium.</hi> Gucl. Nungiac.—<hi>Qui predicationis verbo militum peditumque copias undicunque contraxit praefatoſque haereticos expugnavit. Verùm id fruſtrà. Nam ut ſui compotes facti ſunt, ſe in erroris priſtini volutabro revolverunt.</hi> Robert. Altiſſiordor. <hi>citat. ab</hi> Uſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer. <hi>ibid</hi> p. 244.</note> 
               <hi>Henry,</hi> before Abbot of <hi>Clairvoux</hi> and now a Cardinal, was ſent by the Pope into <hi>Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coigny</hi> againſt them <hi>Anno</hi> 1181. where he over-powred them indeed by his grear <hi>Army;</hi> but to no purpoſe; for aſſoon as they were got out of his Clutches, they openly profeſt their Faith again. <hi>Anno</hi> 1182. a great many of theſe poor people were <hi>burnt</hi> in ſeveral Parts of <hi>France;</hi> and applications were made to <hi>Hen.</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond (under pretence of a <hi>Viſion)</hi> that he would do the ſame thing in <hi>England: But he would not ſuffer it to be done in his Country, though there were abundance of that perſwaſion there,</hi> ſaith <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tempus vero ne quo haec viſio contigerat, erat tunc quando Publicani comturebantur in quam plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus locis per regnum</hi> Franciae, <hi>quod Rex</hi> (Henricus) <hi>nullo modo fieri permiſit in terra ſua, licet ibi eſſent perplurimi.</hi> Roger. <hi>de</hi> Hoveden. <hi>in fine Anni</hi> 1182.</note> 
               <hi>Hoveden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is no great honour to the Doctrine of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation, that when it came into the world it ſoon coſt Bloud; nor could it prevail till the party which upheld it made its way by Fire and Sword. The truths of Chriſtianity were not propagated by ſuch barbarous
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:97031:34"/>
methods; for there is ſuch a natural lovelyneſs in Truth, as renders it worthy of all acceptation? and ſo much the more, for not ſtanding in need of Sanguinary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings. But error is not eaſily ſupported any other way; and 'tis a ſign of a falſe Doctrine, when it muſt be forced upon the conſcience by cutting of throats. However the Perſecutions that were now, did this good, that the true Faith was confirmed by New Martyrdomes; and recovered ſome of that Luſtre under butchering Popes, which Chriſtianity had gained under <hi>Nero.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lucius</hi> the Third was now Pope, who in the year 1183 (as <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad abolendum diverſarum haereſum pravitae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, quae in pleriſque mundi partibus modernis caepit temporibus pullulare,</hi> &amp;c—<hi>Imprimis</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharos <hi>&amp;</hi> Patarenos <hi>&amp; eos qui ſe Humiliatos vel Pauperes de</hi> Lugduno <hi>falſo nomine menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untur, Paſſaginos, Joſepinos, Arnaldiſtas, perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuo decernimus Anathemati ſubjacere.</hi> Lucii 3. <hi>Decret.</hi> Labbaei <hi>Concil.</hi> Tom. 10.</note> 
               <hi>L'abbey</hi> computes it) iſſued out another Anathema, for the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of divers <hi>Hereſies</hi> (ſo called) <hi>which in thoſe times grew in moſt parts of the World;</hi> and he particularly mention'd the <hi>Cathariſts,</hi> the <hi>Patarens,</hi> and thoſe that were called the <hi>Humble Men, or the Poor of</hi> Lions; that is, the <hi>Albigenſes,</hi> who ſtifly oppoſed, among other Errors, that of Tranſubſtantiation. One <hi>Outward</hi> Advantage which did help to make them ſo very Numerous and Spreading was the Protection they found from divers Princes and Great Men, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly <hi>Raymund</hi> Earl of <hi>Tolouſe,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> King of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon,</hi> as <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nec mirum tam latè eam labem fuiſſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſam, cum</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bigenſium <hi>ſecta a primo exortu principium vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorum (quae magna Pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es eſt) favore fuerit armata:</hi> Toloſatis <hi>primi Comitis, deinde Fuxenſis, Biterarum &amp; Convenarum. Acceſſit</hi> Petri Aragoniae <hi>regis patrocinium.</hi> Joan. Marian. <hi>praefat. ad</hi> Lucum. Tùdenſem. <hi>Vide &amp; Concil</hi> Lavaureſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no 1214. <hi>Item</hi> Math. Paris <hi>in</hi> Joanne.</note> 
               <hi>Joannes Mariana</hi> doth confeſs: And with this agrees the Account given of this matter by the Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous <note n="*" place="margin">Thuan <hi>Hiſt.</hi> lib. 6. <hi>ad</hi> An. 1550.</note> 
               <hi>Thuanus.</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Citat. in C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Teſt.</hi> pag. 1526.</note> 
               <hi>Jacobus de Rebira,</hi> the French Kings Secretary, adds, <hi>that they were in great Eſteem, above the ordinary Prieſts, for Wit and Learning that they were Honoured by their very Enemies; that they were freed from common Burdens and Impoſitions; and that every ones ſafety ſeem'd to have been wrapped up in Theirs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:97031:35"/>
The growing intereſt, and great ſtrength, which the Adverſaries of Tranſubſtantiation now had inraged the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> ſo, that in the Papacy of <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third they were forced to the moſt <hi>extream,</hi> but moſt <hi>diſhonourable</hi> ſhiſts: And even when they had ſo much buſineſs in their Hands about the recovering of <hi>Paleſtine</hi> from the <hi>Turks. The Hereſie at</hi> Tolouſe <hi>being ſo increaſed</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Non enim diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptationibus verborum tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tùm, verùm eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am armis opus fuit; adeò ino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leverat tanta haereſis (apud <hi>Toloſani.) Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina</hi> in vitâ <hi>Innocentii 3.</hi>
               </note> (ſaith Platina) <hi>there was need, not of Diſputations, but of Arms too.</hi> And the Zealots for Tranſubſtantiatiation had now got a <hi>Tool</hi> for their turn at <hi>Rome;</hi> this <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third, made Pope <hi>Anno</hi> 1198. a young Man, about Thirty years of Age, Hot, Fierce, Imperious, and (as far as I find by his Speeches in the <hi>Lateran)</hi> Ignorant enough. This youngſter ſoon laid about him, and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a long and bloody War againſt the <hi>Albigenſes. Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus</hi> in his Sixth Book ſhews particularly, what outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges his General <hi>Simon Montfort</hi> committed in ſeveral places of <hi>France,</hi> Hanging, Beheading, Burning, and making the moſt horrible Slaughters wherever he went; throwing into the Flames at <hi>Paris</hi> ſeveral Prieſts too, that were of the <hi>Albigenſes</hi> perſwaſion. The way of dealing with them in <hi>England</hi> was, to burn them in the Shoulders or Foreheads with a Red Hot Iron: And the ſame Author ſhews you, how the Pope uſed the Earl of <hi>Tolouſe,</hi> and the King of <hi>Aragon</hi> alſo. And <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Binii <hi>notae in Concil.</hi> Lateran.</note> tells us, out of <hi>Mathew Paris,</hi> how that the Earldome of <hi>Tolouſe</hi> was given to <hi>Montfort</hi> for almoſt twelve years ſervice againſt the <hi>Albigenſes,</hi> after the War againſt them had been firſt begun by Pope <hi>Innocent:</hi> As great a War ſaith <hi>Thuanus,</hi> as that was which was raiſed againſt the <note place="margin">Thuan. <hi>Praefat.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Saracens:</hi> But, as he ingenuouſly acknowledgeth the Reſult of the War was this, that great Numbers of the <hi>Albigenſes</hi> were Kill'd, Routed, Stript of their Eſtates and Dignities, and ſcatter'd up and down into ſeveral quarters, but not <hi>convinced</hi> by theſe outrageous Courſes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:97031:35"/>
After all which, <hi>Anno</hi> 1215 (the year before God took this Bloody Pope out of the World) that Great Council met at the <hi>Lateran,</hi> wherein the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation was decreed in expreſs Terms.</p>
            <p>It had been a wonder indeed, if at laſt one poor De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree could not have been got for the eſtabliſhing of it, after ſo many years had been ſpent in Arts and Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence firſt to form it, and then to bring it to ſome perfection. Yet I muſt deſire you to note, that this Decree was the <hi>Pope</hi>'s only, not <note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Venère multa tum quidem in conſultationem, nec decerni tamen quicquam apertè potuit.</hi> Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina <hi>de vita</hi> Innocent.</p>
                  <p>3. <hi>—Facto prius ab ipſo Papa exhortationis ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mone, recitata ſunt in pleno Concilio capitula 70. quae aliis placabilia, aliis videbantur Oneroſa.</hi> Math. Par. <hi>in</hi> Joanne <hi>ad Ann.</hi> 1215.</p>
               </note> the <hi>Councils. Platina</hi> tells us, that <hi>nothing was openly Decreed by this Council, though many things were propoſed to their conſideration.</hi> And <hi>Mathew Paris</hi> aſſures us, that the <hi>Pope having made a Speech to them, Seventy Chapters or Heads</hi> (which now are called the Decrees of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil) <hi>were read before them, which were acceptable to ſome, but ſeemed burdenſome to others.</hi> 'Tis plain, that there are no Acts of this Council extant, which ſhew in the leaſt, that any of the things propoſed were ſo much as <hi>debated;</hi> but the Council roſe before they had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd matters, or came to any Solemn Concluſion af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Synodical manner. The Reaſons of it ſeem to have been, partly becauſe there were then Wars in <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly</hi> (as <hi>Platina</hi> and others relate) which extreamly frightned that Pope, and partly too, becauſe ſome of the Council were diſſatisfied as to the Reaſonableneſs of the Popes Propoſals (as <hi>Mathew Paris</hi> well obſerved) and it ſeems not improbable, but that they might be diſſatisfied as to the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation in particular. I will not be poſitive in this, but leave it to be conſider'd by Learned Men: But the ground of my Conjecture is this, becauſe <hi>Sabellicus</hi> ſpeaking of this <hi>Lateran</hi> Council expreſſy affirms, that <hi>at that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:97031:36"/>
time the peſtilent Hereſie of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sunt &amp;</hi> Crucigeri Lateranenſi <hi>conventu probati ſupremo</hi> Innocentii <hi>Anno, qui ſalutis fuit humanae duodecies centeſimus ac quintus decimus, quum peſtilen; eſſet</hi> Romae <hi>Haereſis orta, mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſque ex ea motus extitiſſet, multi qui tum fortè in urbe erant, cruce ſignati, in</hi> Syram, <hi>credo, ituri, aut certè inde reverſi,</hi> Innocentii <hi>hortatu peſtem illam in horas gliſcentem naviter extinaeerunt; quidam</hi> Albienſem <hi>ab autore, ut reor, eam nuncuparunt Haereſim.</hi> Sabellic. Aene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad. 9. lib. 6. p. 736. <hi>edit.</hi> Baſil.</note> Albigenſes (as he terms it) <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd at</hi> Rome, and that <hi>a great Commotion hapned there upon it, which the Pope was forced to put an End by the help of the Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geri,</hi> that is, a ſort of Souldiers that had liſted themſelves under the Sign of the Croſs for an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition into the Holy Land. And if it were thus, as very likely it was, 'tis no wonder that the Pope and his great Council ſhould break up in ſome haſte. If you ask, how it might come to paſs, that the Popes Decrees were not publickly oppoſed while the Council was yet ſitting? The Reaſon is evident enough. This <hi>Innocent</hi> was a moſt Proud, Inſolent, Cruel Man: One that had depoſed I know not how many Biſhops, that had deprived <hi>Otho</hi> the Emperour of the Romans, that had huff'd <hi>Henry</hi> the Emperour of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> that had Excommunicated King <hi>John</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> that had arrogantly treated the Kings of <hi>Bohemia, Portugal, Sici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, France</hi> and <hi>Aragon;</hi> that had robb'd the Earl of <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſe</hi> of all his Poſſeſſions; that had Barbarouſly uſed the <hi>Albigenſes</hi> by the flaſhing and burning Zeal of the Crucigeri; and that now, in the time of the <hi>Lateran</hi> Council, was ſtrengthned at <hi>Rome</hi> with Great Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of them, ready to do any miſchief that he ſhould command them. And then, how could it be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but that the whole Council would be over-awed into ſilence, ſuppoſing any of them were againſt the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Tranſubſtantiation? Eſpecially if you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that in the Third Head of his Propoſals he had Condemned all Hereticks, all that were but ſuſpected of Hereſie, all that ſhew'd any Humanity to Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks; not excepting Princes themſelves, over whom
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:97031:36"/>
he claimed a Power, and declared his purpoſes not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Excommunicate them, but moreover to abſolve their Subjects from their Allegiance, and to give away their Territories.</p>
            <p>By this it appears, what little Reaſon our Romaniſts have to pretend the Authority of this <hi>Lateran</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil for their beloved Tranſubſtantiation, and how little they gain by it upon a ſtrict Examination of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. After all the Arts and Toyl of ſo many years to bring this ſtrange conceit into ſome ſhape, and to Cure thoſe Flaws which all diſcerning and upright Men found in the formation of it: After ſuch various Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods uſed to get a Decree for it, and to obtrude it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an eaſie World in times of Ignorance: After ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Hoſtile and Barbarous Courſes practiced in ſeveral Parts of Chriſtendome upon thoſe who ſaw the falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of it, and would not ſubmit to the Innovation: After ſo much Blood ſhed, and ſo many Lives taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in that unjuſt Cauſe: The Patrons of it having got at length a promiſing opportunity of ſettling it in this Great Council at <hi>Rome,</hi> and under the awe of a moſt Heady and Inſolent Pope, they providentially <hi>miſt</hi> of their deſigns at laſt. In <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf many <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed</hi> it with <hi>Rage,</hi> probably divers of the <hi>Council</hi> did not at all like it; to be ſure they roſe without confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it by a Synodical <hi>Decree;</hi> ſo that it had no Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority but the Pope's <hi>own,</hi> and <hi>that</hi> Pope's too, who warranted <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Treaſon</hi> in Subjects, and made it the great buſineſs and <hi>Delight</hi> of his own Life du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his Papacy.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Threats</hi> would not do the work yet. For <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Math. Par. <hi>in</hi> Hen. 2. <hi>ad An.</hi> 1223.</note> 
               <hi>Paris</hi> tells us, that <hi>Anno 1223 the</hi> Albigenſes <hi>choſe one</hi> Bartholomaeus <hi>their Anti-Pope, in</hi> Bulgary, Croatia, Dalmatia, <hi>and thoſe parts about</hi> Hungary; where their Opinion prevailed ſo, that many Biſhops and others a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:97031:37"/>
with them. Moreover, that <hi>Anno</hi> 1234. they had Biſhops of their perſwaſion in <hi>Spain,</hi> and that an infinite Number of them was kill'd in <hi>Alemannia</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> the ſame year. Beſides, the Writings of <hi>Lucus Iudenſis</hi> about <hi>Anno</hi> 1240. and of <hi>Petrus Pilichdorfius</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Anno</hi> 1450. both <hi>againſt</hi> the <hi>Albigenſes,</hi> do plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew, that notwithſtanding the Decree of <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third, the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation was ſtill vigorouſly <hi>reſiſted</hi> in very many places of the World, and even where the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> carried great Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. But I muſt not forget a memorable Story of <hi>Guido Groſſus,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Narbonne Anno</hi> 1268. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſhews, how little He and the Divines at <hi>Paris</hi> then hearkned to the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, notwithſtanding all that had been done by Pope <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las</hi> the Second, <hi>Gregory</hi> the Seventh, and <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third; and when you have conſider'd it well, I leave you to judge too by the way, whether the judgment of the Popes, tho' in <hi>Council,</hi> was in thoſe days thought <hi>Infallible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Guido Groſſus</hi> going to ſee Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the Fourth, his Old familiar acquaintance, and diſcourſing in his Court with a certain Learned perſon, could not forbear declaring his ſenſe about the Euchariſt, which was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly <hi>repugnant</hi> to Tranſubſtantiation. For his Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was that <hi>the Body of our Lord is not eſſentially in the Euchariſt, but only as the thing ſignified is under the ſign:</hi> To which it ſeems he added, that <hi>this was the Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Opinion at</hi> Paris. After <hi>Guido</hi>'s return home, <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens</hi> heard of this, and wrote him a chiding Letter, wherein he inſinuated alſo, that if he perſitted in that Opinion, he would be in danger of loſing his <hi>Dignity</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Euchar.</hi> lib. 3. P. 973.</note> and <hi>Office:</hi> This Letter the Learned <hi>Albertinus</hi> hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us a Copy of out of a Manuſcript in Pope <hi>Clement's</hi> Regiſter; and the thing is further atteſted by Monſieur
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:97031:37"/>
               <hi>I Arroque</hi> in his Hiſtory of the Euchariſt, lately rendred into Engliſh, and juſt fallen into my hands, where you may ſee it at large; though the principal part of it is, what I have already related. I <hi>add</hi> out of <hi>both;</hi> that though the Archbiſhop anſwer'd the Popes Letter with ſome Caution and Fear, yet in his Anſwer he ſaid e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to clear and juſtifie his own Opinion <hi>againſt</hi> Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation. For ſaith he, the Body of Chriſt is ſo called Four ways. 1. In reſpect of <hi>Similitude;</hi> as the Species of Bread and Wine, and that <hi>improperly</hi> 2. It is taken for the <hi>Material</hi> Fleſh of Jeſus Chriſt, which was taken of the Bleſſed Virgin: And this ſignification is proper. 3. For the <hi>Church,</hi> in regard of its Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Union (with Chriſt.) 4. For the <hi>Spiritual Fleſh</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, which is Meat indeed; And it is ſaid of thoſe who Eat this Fleſh <hi>Spiritually,</hi> that they do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Truth of the Fleſh and Blood of our Saviour, which, as it overthrows the Dream of Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo it is the very Language of the Ancients, <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Alexandrinus,</hi> S. <hi>Jerome,</hi> S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> S. <hi>Austin,</hi> and others, who did diſtinguiſh Chriſt's <hi>Natural</hi> Body which was of the Virgin, from that <hi>Spiritual</hi> Body which is receiv'd at the Euchariſt; as you may ſee plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in that excellent little Book called the DIALLAC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TICON, which God be thanked is now reprinted at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi> A Book written as Biſhop <hi>Coſins</hi> tells us, by Dr. <hi>Poinet</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> a little before Biſhop <hi>Jewels</hi> Apology came out. <hi>Caſſander</hi> and other Divines abroad Extolled it deſervedly. The late <hi>Sa. Oxon</hi> (if I may rank him among ſuch Company) takes notice of it; but <note place="margin">P. 61.</note> ſays withal, I have not the Book by me: And I verily believe it; for had he ever ſeen or read that Book, I am apt to think he would hardly have wrote his own; at leaſt, not that part of it; the force whereof is quite deſtroy'd by the <hi>Diallacticon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:97031:38"/>
But not to digreſs further, eſpecially when I am near the <hi>End</hi> of my buſineſs. Though in the Thirteenth and Fourteenth Centuries Tranſubſtantiation was the common Tenent, yet I cannot find that it paſt in thoſe times for a certain <hi>Article</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> determined by the Publick Authority of the Church, but as a <hi>probable Opinion</hi> only, as they thought then. Thoſe many difficult Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences (about <hi>Eating, Digeſting, Voiding</hi> the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whether by <hi>Men</hi> or <hi>Beaſts,</hi> and the like) which the ſubtle Schoolmen met with in managing that Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, do plainly ſhew that the thing was not yet clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed beyond all Reaſon of doubting, nor ſetled by any Authority, which might be preſumed ſufficient to require their ſubmiſſion. It is well known, that the Famous Doctor of <hi>Sorbon Johannes Pariſicnſis</hi> near the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat.</hi> Joan. <hi>edit.</hi> Londin. 1686.</note> year 1300. though he profeſt to hold Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet he held it only as a current <hi>Opinion;</hi> he was ſo far from urging it as an Article of Faith, that he propoſed <hi>another</hi> way of explaining the real preſence, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>Myſtical Union</hi> of the Sacred Symbols with Chriſt's perſon, which <hi>Rupertus</hi> and others had ſpoke of long <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In praeſentia Collegii Magiſtrorum in Theologia dictum eſt, utrumque modum poneudi Corpus Chriſti eſſe in altari, tenet pro Opinione probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li, &amp; approbat utrumque per—&amp; dicta Sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Dicit tamen quod nullus eſt determinatus per Eccleſiam, &amp; ideo nullum cadere ſub fide; &amp; ſi aliter dixiſſet, minus benè dixiſſet, &amp; qui alitur dieunt, minus bene dicunt, &amp; qui deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate aſſereret alterutrum proeciſè cadere ſub fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, incur reret ſententiam Canonis, vel Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matis. Cenſura Facultatis Theologioe,</hi> Pariſ.</note> before. And when the Doctors of Divinity at <hi>Paris</hi> had Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined his determination, they gave this Cenſure of him at the End of it, <q>that he had done well in delivering both as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable Opinions, not ſo deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd by the Church as to be thought either of them an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of Faith: and (ſay they) if he had ſaid other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, he would not have ſaid ſo well; and they who do ſpeak otherwiſe ſpeak amiſs, and whoſoever ſhall peremptorily aſſert either Opinion to be preciſely of Faith ought to incur the Sentence of the Canon, or Excommunication.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:97031:38"/>
I ſhall not need to trouble you with more Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, how the oppoſite Doctrine to Tranſubſtantiation paſſed on ſtill through a crowd of Adverſaries down to the times of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> which began preſently after <hi>Anno</hi> 1500. You find ready at hand, in the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of Tranſubſtantiation I mentioned before, in Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Coſins, Albertine,</hi> and <hi>l'Arroque</hi> (not to ſpeak of any more) not only the Names of ſome particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but an account too of Great Numbers of people in <hi>Bohemia, France, England,</hi> &amp;c. Who notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Threats and Oppreſſions perſiſted ſtill in the True Faith, and tranſmitted it down to Poſterity. I ſhall only add, what the Learned Monſieur <hi>Alixius</hi> (now in <hi>England)</hi> hath particularly proved in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to the Determination of <hi>Joannes Pariſienſis;</hi> that though the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation prevailed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the fantaſtical School-men from time to time, yet they found ſo many perplexities in it, as did put all the Wits they had upon the Tenters; the moſt ſedate and intelligent Men among them own'd it only as an <hi>Opinion</hi> they had receiv'd by <hi>Tradition,</hi> not as an Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Faith declared by any Authentick and Obligato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Decrees of the <hi>Church:</hi> And being a common Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion they would not contradict it; though ſome of them affirm'd, that <hi>the Permanency of the Subſtance of the Bread and Wine is not impoſſible,</hi> nor contrary to Reaſon or to the Authority of the Bible; nay, that it was the moſt <hi>Rational Opinion ſo that had they been Popes, they would have defined it.</hi> As for the definitions of <hi>Nicolas</hi> the Second, and <hi>Gregory</hi> the Seventh, they could not ſee how thoſe did inforce the belief of the Annihilation of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the Elements; but of a Subſtantial <hi>Preſence</hi> only, which they thought might eaſily be admitted, though <hi>Permanency</hi> of the Subſtance in the Symbols
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:97031:39"/>
ſhould be believed too. As for the Decree of <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third, they laid no great weight upon it, becauſe it was not the deliberate and Synodical determination of the whole Council, and I would ſain know, whether our preſent Romaniſts will inſiſt upon the Authority of it, ſeeing it aſſerts with a Witneſs the <hi>Depoſing Power;</hi> which the <hi>Gallican</hi> Clergy did <hi>Anno</hi> 1682. Condemn, as Erroneous, and Injurious to Princes. As for the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Conſtance</hi> which Condemned <hi>Wicleffe</hi> for denying the Corporal preſence and Tranſubſtantiation <hi>An.</hi> 1415. it was ever thought by many Romaniſts themſelves to be of <hi>queſtionable</hi> Authority, becauſe it Condemned and Depoſed the Pope too. And as touching the Council of <hi>Florence Anno</hi> 1439. However the Doctrine of the Sacrament was <hi>offer'd</hi> to their conſideration; yet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Tranſubſtantiation was in the leaſt <hi>Defined</hi> then.</p>
            <p>This is the Truth of the Caſe, as far as I can find up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſtricteſt Enquiry. By which it appears, not only what an Innovation the Myſterious Notion of Tranſubſtantiation is, but alſo how this Innovation in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas'd and ſwe;;'d about 120 years a go, at the Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Seſſion of the Council of <hi>Trent;</hi> when that which before had been the private <hi>Opinion</hi> of ſome fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyful Men, was adopted into the Church as a neceſſary Article of <hi>Faith,</hi> that <hi>by the Conſecration of the Bread and Wine ther is a Converſion of their whole Subſtance into the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Chriſts Body and Blood,</hi> and thereupon they Define that <hi>whoſoever ſhould deny either of theſe Two Things; 1. That the whole Chriſt, his Body and Blood together with his Soul and Divinity is truly, really, and Subſtantially contain'd in the Eucharist:</hi> Or, Secondly <hi>that ſhall deny this wonderful Converſion of the whole Subſtance of Bread into Chriſt's Body, and of the whole Subſtance of Wine into his Blood, the Species only of Bread and Wine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:97031:39"/>
ſhould be Anathematiz'd.</hi> Here were two New Opinions made Articles of Faith by a ſtrange Synodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Definition: The Corporal Preſence, and Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation. The Firſt, as I have ſhew'd you, was ſtart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Paſchaſius Ratbertus</hi> in the <hi>9th.</hi> Century; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was introduced in the Eleventh: Both very Late and Modern Imaginations in Compariſon of the True Faith of the Church which was, by all that I can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover, held without interruption for about the ſpace of the firſt 800 years, and is ſtill proſeſt by us of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and by other Proteſtant Churches. The Two Opinions I ſpeak of, were no ſooner vended, but they were vigorouſly Oppos'd, as New Errours: And though by Arts and Violence, with the help of Time, they did ſpread in ſome Parts, yet ſtill they were but private Mens <hi>Opinions:</hi> And though afterwards they came to be Countenanced by ſome that were in Authority, yet they were not Definitions agreed upon after a Synodical manner by any Council of unqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Authority. Nay, though they were eſpouſed by ſome fierce Popes, and for that ſole Reaſon were main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd by divers Doctors of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to what others believed, yet at the ſame time thoſe Doctors reckoned them not (eſpecially that of Tranſubſtantiation) among the neceſſary Articles of the Chriſtian Faith. They were made ſo by the late pack't Council of <hi>Trent;</hi> who by ſo doing neceſſarily cauſed irreparable breaches in the Churches of Chriſt, and brought a viſible Scandal upon Chriſtianity it ſelf by eſtabliſhing ſuch nauſeous Opinions, as are enough to turn any Mens Stomachs, that will but hearken to their Senſes and Reaſon.</p>
            <p>I know the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> did deliver this Doctrine, as the Catholick Faith, <hi>which had always been believed
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:97031:40"/>
by the Church</hi> (as they were pleaſed to ſay) and becauſe they ſaid it, the Romaniſts generally think themſelves obliged to believe it. But the Novelty is Evident; and 'twere no impoſſible matter to ſhew, that even <hi>ſince</hi> the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> ſeveral Great Men in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> have not been pleaſed with it. Mr. <hi>Alixius</hi> mentions Two beſides the now living Author of the late Learned Treatiſe of Tranſubſtantiation, <hi>viz. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus de Marca,</hi> and <hi>Barnes</hi> a Benedictine, who held that Tranſubſtantiation is not now an Article of Faith. <note place="margin">Alix. <hi>ubiſupr.</hi> pag. 80.</note> Nay, to be free with you, the preſent Romaniſts are ſo troubled with ſuch intricate and inſeparable difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties throughout the whole point, that I am tempted to believe many of them ſecretly wiſh it had been o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe defined: But now it is done, they will not Retract for fear of loſing the Credit of Infallibility, which ſupports all.</p>
            <p>Sir, I promiſed you in the beginning of this Letter to take notice of what hath been ſaid upon this Point in ſome late Pamphlets; and the Task will be the leſs, becauſe the Learned Author of the <hi>Veteres Vindicati</hi> has been before hand with me, who have been forced to wait till this Point fell in my way, in that Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Account which I undertook in my Firſt Letter. However I will not make this Swell, but deſire your Patience till another time: Perhaps ſome brisk Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man may afford me ſome New Work; and then I may Anſwer all under one.</p>
            <p>In the mean time I have a requeſt to you. My Second Letter you know about <hi>Images</hi> was quarrell'd with by one, to whom I gave a Civil Return, without receiving yet any ſort of Reply, that I know of. 'Tis odds but he will be Quarrelling with this too, becauſe it bears hard upon a Mighty Point of Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:97031:40"/>
Therefore if you chance to know him, be pleas'd to whiſper him in the Ear, that if he will keep cloſe to matter of Fact, and uſe Genuine Authors, and forbear Reproachful and Unhandſome Language, and Deal with me like a Scholar, he ſhall certainly find me a fair Adverſary. But if he ſhall run out into things that are impertinent and quite out of the way, you may wiſh him to have a care, leaſt ſome Honeſt <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Footman</hi> give him a Breathing. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your most Faithful and Obedient Servant.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>May 11. 1688.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:97031:41"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97031:41"/>
            <head>BOOKS Printed for and Sold by <hi>Ben. Griffin,</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Griffin</hi> in the <hi>Great Old-Baily</hi> near <hi>Ludgate-hill.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Hiſtory and Antiquities of <hi>Rutlandſhire</hi> col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected from the Records, Ancient Manuſcripts, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents on the Place, and other Authors, by <hi>J. W.</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Diſcourſe of the Sacrament of the Lords Supper,</hi> wherein the Faith of the Catholick Church concerning that Myſtery is explained, proved, and vindicated after an intelligent, catechetical, and eaſie manner, by <hi>Edw. Pelling,</hi> Chaplain to his Grace the Duke of Somerſet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Regular Chriſtians daily Sacrifice,</hi> or a Collection of Prayers chieſly out of <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalms, and the reſt of the Common-Prayer; to be uſed by the People in their private Devotions, on all ordinary and ſpecial oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions; with a particular Office for Sacrament-Days, by <hi>Edw. Pelling,</hi> Chaplain to his Grace the D. of <hi>Somerſet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Sermon preach'd at the</hi> Abbey, <hi>July</hi> 1685. being the Thankſgiving day for his Majeſties Victory over the Rebells, by <hi>Edw. Pelling,</hi> Chaplain to his Grace the D. of <hi>Somerſet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Sermon preached at St.</hi> Georges <hi>Church at</hi> Windſor, <hi>Sept.</hi> 26. 1685. by <hi>Edw. Pelling</hi> Chaplain to his Grace the D. of <hi>Somerſet.</hi> Printed by Order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Antiquity of the Proteſtant Religion,</hi> with an anſwer to Mr. <hi>Sclater</hi>'s Reaſons, and to the Collectioins made by the Author of a Pamphlet, Intituled <hi>Nubes Teſtium,</hi> in a Letter to a Perſon of Quality. The Firſt Part.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Antiquity of the Proteſtant Religion concerning Images,</hi> with an Anſwer to the Collections made by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Pamphlet Intituled <hi>Nubes Teſtium,</hi> In a Letter to a Perſon of Quality. The Second Part.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Third Letter to a Perſon of Quality,</hi> being a Vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:97031:42"/>
of the former, In an Anſwer to a late Pamphlet, Intituled <hi>a Diſcourſe of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Images.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Fourth Letter to a Perſon of Quality;</hi> being an Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Account of the Doctrine of the Sacrament from the Primitive Times to the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> ſhewing the Novelty of Tranſubſtantiation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diallaction Viri Boni &amp; Literati de Veritate, Natura, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Subſtantia Corporis &amp; Sanguinis Chriſti in Euchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Georgii Buchanani Scoti Poemata in Tres Partes digeſta. Pars Prima Pſalmorum Davidis paraphraſis poetica, Jeph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſive Votum, Tragaedia. Baptiſtes ſive Calumnia. Pars Secunda, Franciſcanus &amp; Fratres. Elegiarum Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. Sylvarum Liber. Hendecaſyllabωn Liber. Iam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bωn Liber. Epigrammatum Libri</hi> III. <hi>Miſcellaneorum Liber. De Sphoera Mundi Lib.</hi> V. <hi>Pars Tertia, Euri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidis Medea; Ejuſdem Alceſtis, utraque Latino carmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne reddita.</hi> G Buchanani <hi>vita ab ipſo ſcripta biennio ante mortem. Adjecta ſunt Paraphraſt Pſalmorum Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta ſingulis Pſalmis praefixa. Item Collectanea quibus Vocabula &amp; Modi loquendi tam Poetici quàm alià diſſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liores, &amp; minùs vulgo obvii, perſpicuè explicantur. Etiam diverſa Carmiuum Genera Margini adjecta. Opera &amp; Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio</hi> N. Chytraei. <hi>His accedunt nunc primùm variae le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiones &amp; conjecturae in partem ſecundam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſſize of Bread</hi> with ſundry good and needful Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for Bakers, Brewers, Inholders, Victuallers, and Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tchers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Perfect Major:</hi> In French and Engliſh. Shewing the eaſieſt way of handling Arms; The Millitary Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with the Manner how to enter into the Field, and to form a Battalion. By <hi>F. d' Morains,</hi> formerly an Officer in the <hi>French</hi> Army's</p>
            <list>
               <item>The French Bible in large 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>French N. Teſtm<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. in large 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>French N. Teſt. in large 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>French Pſalms in 24<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
            </list>
            <p>All of them in a Fair large Letter.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
